<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>blackpath</title>
	<subtitle>Essays and notes about all sorts of things</subtitle>
	<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/"/>
	<updated>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/feed.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Brutal Heroines</title>
		<published>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-07-12-brutal-heroines/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-07-12-brutal-heroines/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;zora_jurassic_rebirth_3.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Scarlett Johansson and Jonathon Bailey stealing a dinosaur egg&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;An average Tuesday afternoon.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw the new Jurassic World (Rebirth) movie this week. It was... not good. It wasn&#x27;t terrible. It just wasn&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;good&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of this is because it was painfully clear that the actors spent a large majority of their on-screen time trying to look awed by the blue props that they were actually interacting with. It&#x27;s damn near impossible for an actor, no matter how good they are, to &lt;em&gt;act&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; under those conditions, I think. It didn&#x27;t help that the blue screens themselves were fairly obvious to anyone who spent their childhood watching movies filmed on location with animatronics. There were differences in lighting between the actors and the background that gave me strong &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;eVTXPUF4Oz4?t=37&quot;&gt;2010-music-video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; vibes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two things in Rebirth that I really appreciated. One was the the stoner boyfriend. He&#x27;s one of the only characters that actually felt like a real person- weird, contradictory, often feckless, stupid, and lazy, but heroic when it matters. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;David_Iacono&quot;&gt;David Iacono&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; did a fantastic job in the role, but it&#x27;s likely that the character enabled a better performance- Xavier is not super bright, so he gets a pass when he fails to look awed enough while staring at a blue wall, and all of his best moments are in dialogue with other characters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing was the character design of Zora. The performance from Scarlett Johansson wasn&#x27;t great (for reasons already mentioned, probably, rather than due to a lack of skill on her part), but the character design was excellent. To explain why, we need to take a look at some iconic films that have female leads. Before I do, it&#x27;s worth noting that this is baseless speculation rooted in my personal experience as an infrequent movie-watcher, rather than a deep dive based on a huge amount of expertise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 80&#x27;s and 90&#x27;s, it seemed like there was a strong shift toward tough female leads that culminated in films like Alien and characters like Sarah Conner. These movies took tropes normally reserved for male action heroes, tailored them a bit for the differences in biology (size, strength etc.) and slapped them onto female action heroes. This mostly worked great- when I&#x27;m watching a story about someone who went through hell and then became a badass, I want to &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it. I want people with some lean muscle, chapped lips, unkempt hair, chewed nails, a big gun, and a variety of canvas bags holding endless supplies of ass-kicking goodies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;terminator_linda_hamilton.webp&quot;  alt=&quot;Linda Hamilton as Sarah Conner in Terminator 2&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;This level of badassery is normally reserved for tanks and Toyota pickups with mounted Mk-19 grenade launchers.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I want someone &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Living with violence &lt;em&gt;makes people weird&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, even if they haven&#x27;t lived with it quite as much as Sarah Conner. People who have adapted to violence jump at fireworks or have strange rules. They speak too bluntly or too casually about tragedies. They sit facing the entrance and get angry over things that seem trivial (unlocked doors, lights left on). They never stand in front of windows. They&#x27;re scared of things no one else notices, and ignore things that everyone else is scared of. They are fundamentally &lt;em&gt;unstable&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, but it&#x27;s an instability that arises from adaptation, rather than biology. When this is done well in film, it gives the story a feel of plausibility that isn&#x27;t easy to verbalize.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You notice it when it&#x27;s gone though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What movies like Aeon Flux or Black Widow don&#x27;t do is show the audience someone &lt;em&gt;who could plausibly exist&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Heroines have perfect curls, perfect skin, and makeup that never runs. These women are &lt;em&gt;presented&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as being a badass assassins, killers, spies, or soldiers, but there is no evidence that they&#x27;ve ever been emotionally or physically impacted by their profession. They&#x27;re not &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, in the way I describe above, they have little muscle, no lines in their faces, and no callous on their hands.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare Michelle Rodriquez&#x27; characters in BloodRayne (Katarin, 2005) and Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons: Honor Among Thieves (Holga, 2023). Holga is blunt, crude, square, muscular, scarred, burned, and often dirty. She&#x27;s got lines in her face because Rodriquez is eighteen years older, but rather than try to conceal them, Rodriquez uses them to her advantage when depicting a character who absolutely &lt;em&gt;would&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; have lines in her face.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;rodriguez_comparison.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Michelle Rodriguez&amp;#x27; character design in BloodRayne and Honor Among Thieves&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;The corset on the left serves no purpose except to push her tits up half an inch.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holga was easily my favorite character in Honor Among Thieves, because she was &lt;em&gt;so&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; well designed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything about the character highlights that she&#x27;s a violent woman who has done and seen some serious shit. The film is still a lighthearted fantasy story, so there are obviously any number of things wrong with her costume (I&#x27;ve read too many posts by &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;acoup.blog&#x2F;2019&#x2F;05&#x2F;03&#x2F;collections-armor-in-order-part-ii&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ACOUP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to believe this armor is realistic), but aesthetically, it &lt;em&gt;works&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. It&#x27;s made out of leather and furs and ragged little odds and ends. She has tattoos and scars (some deliberate, some not) and a weathered tan.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare all of that to Katarin in the movie BloodRayne, and you immediately see the difference. Katarin is slimmer and less muscular, her skin is smooth and unblemished, her hair looks like it was recently washed and combed, and all of her equipment is scratch-free. I&#x27;m not even sure her pants have &lt;em&gt;pockets&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. She looks like a nineteen year old girl going to a halloween party.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zora Bennett in Jurassic World: Rebirth is a mercenary. She&#x27;s supposed to be some flavor of ex-military, now working as a fixer who can move sensitive material and people into and out of locations where they&#x27;re not supposed to be, often while dealing with hostile actors of one sort or another. She&#x27;s been doing it for decades.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;zora_jurassic_rebirth.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Zora from Jurassic Park Rebirth&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Naturally, I assumed she would end up wearing a leather corset at some point.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And blue-screen acting aside, everything about her fits with the image of a middle aged women who has been through hell repeatedly and shot her way back out. I really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; can&#x27;t express how much I appreciate this sort of design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like tits, ass, and beautiful women as much as the next (straight) guy, and I even like it in my movies. But don&#x27;t ruin my immersion by forcing it on a character when it doesn&#x27;t make any sense. If a movie about gangsters has a scene in a strip club, there are going to be a lot of beautiful women with perfect breasts and round asses walking around in lingerie. That&#x27;s awesome. I&#x27;m here for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if the character &lt;em&gt;isn&#x27;t&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a stripper? If her life is hard, demanding, violent, and dirty? Then for fucks sake, &lt;em&gt;give her some scars&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Give her &lt;em&gt;pockets&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Make her skin look rough. Give her bedraggled hair. Have her cuss, mumble, grunt, and spit. Give her &lt;em&gt;wrinkles&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I want lingerie and flawless skin, I can get as much of that as I want. I have unlimited access to the internet. When I want stories, &lt;em&gt;good&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; stories, stories that pull me in and make me believe in another world for two hours, that&#x27;s a much more difficult proposition. I sincerely, deeply appreciate the people who can create those stories, and do it well. For a few hours the other day, despite everything else that was wrong with the film (which was almost everything) Scarlett Johansson did that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>We&#x27;re Probably Screwed</title>
		<published>2025-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-05-28-power/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-05-28-power/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;genie_aladdin.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Genie from the movie Aladdin&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;The face of phenomenal cosmic power.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want power.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say that, you might imagine someone seizing control of a nation (maybe a small one) or gathering followers into some sort of cult, but that&#x27;s not what I&#x27;m thinking of when I say it. Direct power of the sort that autocrats have isn&#x27;t the only sort of power there is. Money is, in a very real way, a sort of power. If you have a million dollars, you can get a lot done. Reputation, connections, family, knowledge, resources, and vehicles, among other things, are power. If you don&#x27;t have a car, no effort of will is going to take you seventy miles down the highway in an hour. A vehicle gives you opportunities that you wouldn&#x27;t otherwise have. If you know a guy who can fix appliances, then when your washer breaks down, you have the power to fix it. It&#x27;s a narrowly applicable power, but power all the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I say &quot;People want power&quot;, I&#x27;m not making any judgement against the people, I&#x27;m stating a fact. Everyone, rich or poor, wants to be able to provide for themselves and their families, and that takes power. It&#x27;s not grand, earth-shaking power, just the mundane, everyday sort of power that allows you to do your job, provide an education for your children, stay warm in winter and cool in summer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is mostly great. If we didn&#x27;t take resources from our environment and use them to do things, we wouldn&#x27;t be human. I&#x27;m not sure it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;the&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; central drive in the species, but it&#x27;s certainly &lt;em&gt;a&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; drive that we have. Of course, I wouldn&#x27;t be writing about this if there wasn&#x27;t some sort of drawback.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people hold an elected position, they have power. They can pass bills if they&#x27;re in congress, set policy for a city if they&#x27;re a mayor, or reorganize the military if they&#x27;re a president. What&#x27;s interesting about this particular flavor of power is that it &lt;em&gt;passes from one person to another&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. If I were a strongman, I&#x27;d have personal power- I can move more, lift more, and am generally more useful (unless I needed to fit in a tight space) than someone who isn&#x27;t as strong as I am. But, crucially, I can&#x27;t give that power to anyone else.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;brian_shaw_deadlift.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Brian Shaw 1128 pound dead lift&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;This is strongman Brian Shaw dead lifting 1,128 pounds. Not the kind of power I&#x27;m talking about, but way more entertaining.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were an elected official, then I may have some measure of personal power (connections and relationships I&#x27;ve made on the job, for example) but much of my power is on loan from the people who elected me. When I pass the position on to someone else, they get the power too. This is also mostly great. It wouldn&#x27;t be much of a position if the occupant didn&#x27;t have the leverage to do their job, and you couldn&#x27;t properly call it a &quot;position&quot; if they didn&#x27;t eventually leave. We &lt;em&gt;want&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; them to have that leverage so that they can get things done, but we &lt;em&gt;also&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; want them to leave at some point so they don&#x27;t go passing it down to their (potentially) incompetent children.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;re basically betting that everyone coming together every few years to vote will produce more competent and less abusive leadership, on average, than if we passed positions along through inheritance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&#x27;s a pretty good bet, honestly. On one hand, we can assume that inheritance is a crap shoot, and any system &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that non-randomly selects leaders from a larger population is probably going to provide better results. On the other, the knowledge that they will have to repeatedly win the approval of the citizenry probably restrains some of the worse impulses of our leaders. It&#x27;s an elegant and effective alternative to autocracy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is not with the drive to acquire power (which is fine) or with democracy in any particular flavor (which is awesome), the problem is when the drive for power comes into contact with elected political positions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one side, we&#x27;ve got the obvious and understandable urge to acquire resources and power, baked into us as a survival strategy in an uncertain world. On the other, we have a system of government designed in such a way that power passes from one individual to another over time. When one meets the other, an interesting thing happens. The people holding these positions don&#x27;t stop acting like people just because they hold a political position. They continue to grasp for any power or leverage they can find, and sometimes, they get it. When they find some loophole, some overlooked clause, some personal connection, or some mutual goal with a powerful political group, they exploit that power as much as they possibly can.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, they&#x27;re people that I would consider generally &quot;good&quot; people (so far as I can see, not knowing many elected officials personally). Sometimes they&#x27;re people I would consider bad. Exploiting those loopholes and connections doesn&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;make&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; you bad or good, it just makes you a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Sometimes they&#x27;re finding little known official powers and abusing them for their own gain, sometimes they do it to protect people or save lives. What I want to stress here is that they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; people. If they&#x27;re people, then they seek control over their environment to make the world better (for some given definition of &quot;better&quot;). This drive doesn&#x27;t change once they&#x27;re in office.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still with me? Good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is the key bit here. Lean in... a little more... ok, too close. This is the important part: &lt;em&gt;some&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of the power that they acquire in their position is &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; power, and some of it &lt;em&gt;isn&#x27;t&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal power, as I said above, is like &lt;em&gt;being strong&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Having friendships with useful people. Owning a car or a house. It&#x27;s some intrinsic feature or resource that you &lt;em&gt;own&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. You might be able to give it away, but you&#x27;re rarely &lt;em&gt;forced to&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The other sort of power that a person might have in an elected position is official power. Official power belongs to your office, your position. You get these powers by holding the position, and you lose them on leaving the position.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While grasping for leverage, resources, or connections, a politician often finds themselves with some new &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; power. Maybe they&#x27;ve cultivated some relationship or learned some secret. But, not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of the power they might acquire is personal. Some of it is going to be official. Maybe they secured a larger budget by creating some new committee, or exploited some old law in a new and interesting fashion, setting a precedent. These powers remain with the office, even after the current office holder leaves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without some system in place to gradually reduce or reverse this expansionary pressure, it seems clear that most elected officials will acquire as much power as they can before leaving, at which point another politician will take their place and continue to drive out the boundaries of their personal (if fleeting) kingdom. Maybe the net effect of hundreds of politicians grasping in every direction for any loose drabs of power is zero. I honestly couldn&#x27;t say.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; zero, though, then the most likely outcome is that the government will &lt;em&gt;always&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; gradually become more powerful, as each individual tries to find some leverage to benefit the themselves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even this isn&#x27;t inherently &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, really. I don&#x27;t like it, but that&#x27;s not the same thing as it being wrong, evil, or inefficient. If we could get lots of good, intelligent people in power to effect change on a large scale, trying to look out for the little guys? Sweet. I&#x27;m a bit of an individualist, so I&#x27;m still not entirely sold on a massively powerful nanny state, but there are certainly worse systems. The problem is that power isn&#x27;t really &quot;good&quot; or &quot;bad&quot;. At the end of the day, it&#x27;s what the military likes to call a &quot;force multiplier.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We solved part of the problem with monarchy, which is that royalty is like a box of chocolates: you never know what you&#x27;re gonna get. We fixed it by literally crowd sourcing a solution through elections. But there is another reason why monarchy is bad. It&#x27;s bad because centralized power multiplies the impact of any particularly good or bad monarch. If your prince is a dick, and wants to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Vlad_the_Impaler&quot;&gt;impale people&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for entertainment purposes, well... he can do that. Sucks to be you. If he&#x27;s a saint who wants to feed everyone, well he can do that too, or at least take a pretty good stab at it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;forest_gump_chocolates.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Forest Gump sitting on a bench with a woman&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;I bet royalty don&#x27;t taste as good as chocolate.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having that much power invested in one individual naturally lends itself to extremes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, in my opinion, is &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Perhaps even &lt;em&gt;very&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; bad. I&#x27;m kidding- it&#x27;s catastrophic. But it&#x27;s one of those slow catastrophes that will sneak up on us. I mean, if a war breaks out, you&#x27;ll have gobs of generals telling people about the global political and military events that led up to it, and buckets of economists eager to explain why trade or resource scarcity is to blame. These are satisfying, actionable causes that we can look into. I can&#x27;t imagine anyone coming forward to argue that natural human drives have combined with representative democracy to gradually centralize power in the hands of fewer individuals, increasing the volatility and reach of the government.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what we can do about it? How could you design a representative government that doesn&#x27;t do this? Is any of this actually a thing in reality, or is it all in my head? I dunno. I have no answers, no ideas about what could or should be done.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#x27;ll leave it at that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>The Deportations Were Illegal</title>
		<published>2025-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-05-15-immigration/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-05-15-immigration/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;trump_bukele_whitehouse.webp&quot;  alt=&quot;Trump and Bukele in the White House&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;There are very few people who can beat Trumps used-car-salesman energy, but Bukele is definitely in the running.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.archives.gov&#x2F;milestone-documents&#x2F;alien-and-sedition-acts&quot;&gt;&quot;Alien Enemies&quot; act&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; was passed in 1798, when the US was dealing with French privateers and on the verge of going to war with France. It was part of a package of bills that, among other things, changed naturalization law, made it illegal to publish &quot;false, scandalous and malicious writing&quot; against the government, and allowed the president to deport citizens of countries that we were at war with. The bit about sedition was weaponized by the aristocratic &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Federalist_Party&quot;&gt;Federalist&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; party as a club against the more small-government &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Democratic-Republican_Party&quot;&gt;Democratic-Republicans&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which apparently screwed them in the elections two years later.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relevant part of the act:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...all natives, citizens, denizens, or subjects of the &lt;strong&gt;hostile nation or government&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, being males of the age of fourteen years and upwards, who shall be within the United States, and not actually naturalized, shall be liable to be apprehended, restrained, secured and removed, as alien enemies. [emphasis mine]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems pretty clear to me. If we&#x27;re at war with a foreign nation, we obviously have an interest in keeping their citizens out of our country, or at least keeping tabs on them to ensure they don&#x27;t sabotage infrastructure or something. This law has only been used three times- in the war of 1812, World War 1 and World War 2. It&#x27;s not clear how many people were detained and deported in 1812, and it&#x27;s use in World War 1 was limited to about 6000 German immigrants&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. The most well known use was during World War 2, when the government interned about 112,000 Japanese, Italian, and German immigrants in &quot;military facilities, gyms, jails, fair grounds and racetracks&quot;, according to the NYTimes&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth time the Alien Enemies act was used was on March 15th, 2025.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 15th, Donald Trump issued an executive order titled &quot;&lt;em&gt;Invocation of the Alien Enemies Act Regarding the Invasion of The United States by Tren De Aragua&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&quot;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This order says that Tren de Aragua (a Venezuelan drug cartel) is inextricably wrapped up with the Venezualan government, and they&#x27;re commiting crimes in the US and bringing drugs across the border. So, because the cartel is enmeshed in the Venezualan government, and they&#x27;re doing bad stuff in the US, then they&#x27;re &lt;em&gt;sorta&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;kinda&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a hostile foreign governement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Venezuala] is a hybrid criminal state that is perpetrating an invasion of and predatory incursion into the United States, and which poses a substantial danger to the United States.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a... really impressive series of contortions, honestly. This executive order links a cartel to Venezuala (fair enough), then claims that &lt;em&gt;the actions of the cartel&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; constitute an assault on the US &lt;em&gt;by Venezuala&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, which neatly makes Venezuala a &quot;hostile nation or government&quot; for the purposes of the Alien Enemies act. You might wonder why, if we&#x27;re being invaded by a hostile power, we&#x27;re not deploying soldiers to Venezuala. I wonder why too. Not one else seems to be asking that question, and the reason why they aren&#x27;t asking it is &lt;em&gt;because Venezuala isn&#x27;t attacking us&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals who may (we&#x27;ll get to this in a bit) be associated with Tren de Aragua, are committing crimes in the US. If individuals are commiting crimes, we have procedures in place to deal with that- arrests, fines, imprisonment, and maybe deportation back to Venezuala. If a hostile nation is attacking us, we have procedures for that too- diplomatic and trade sanctions, international pressure, and war. But the administration doesn&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; war with Venezuala. What they wanted was a way to avoid due process for the people they were about to send to a Salvadoran death camp.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;cecot_prison_cell.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;CECOT prison cell&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;One that doesn&#x27;t provide mattresses for their quadruple-stacked steel bunks.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The executive order was published at 3:53PM&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and an hour and a half later, the first two planes left for the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Terrorism_Confinement_Center&quot;&gt;CECOT&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; prison facility in El Salvador. That afternoon around 6:48PM, Judge James Boasberg, hearing an &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;assets.aclu.org&#x2F;live&#x2F;uploads&#x2F;2025&#x2F;03&#x2F;COMPLAINT-J.G.G.-v.-TRUMP.pdf&quot;&gt;emergency petition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from the ACLU regarding five of the men detained, ordered any flights out of the country that contain deportees under the Alien Enemies act to remain grounded, and for any flights that were in the air to return. The court emailed officials and posted the order online around 7:26PM.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten minutes later, the last plane took off, and, in direct violation of this order, all three planes landed in El Salvador early the next morning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration still hasn&#x27;t released detailed information about the people who were sent to El Salvador, although CBS managed to find a list of names&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and spent some time looking for criminal records. They found that nearly 75% of the men deported didn&#x27;t have one&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;6&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, and of the remainder, a fair number only had minor, non-violent offenses (shoplifting, trespassing etc). If these people have committed crimes that CBS couldn&#x27;t find, no one in the administration has bothered to release that information. Likely because it doesn&#x27;t exist.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No State shall make or enforce any law which shall abridge the privileges or immunities of citizens of the United States; &lt;strong&gt;nor shall any State deprive any person&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; nor deny to any person within its jurisdiction the equal protection of the laws.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
-- &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;constitution.congress.gov&#x2F;browse&#x2F;essay&#x2F;amdt14-S1-3&#x2F;ALDE_00013743&#x2F;&quot;&gt;14th Amendment of the US Constitution&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason why we &lt;em&gt;have&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a process for dealing with criminals is so that we don&#x27;t unfairly jail or punish people who haven&#x27;t committed any crimes. That process is the right of all people in the United States, citizen or not. If that process had been followed (if our &lt;em&gt;laws&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; had been followed), we wouldn&#x27;t be guessing about the identities of these people and journalists wouldn&#x27;t be scrutinizing public records to try to find criminal records (and we wouldn&#x27;t be paying El Salvador $6 million&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#7&quot;&gt;7&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; to jail suspected Venezuelan gang members).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month after the planes left, Trump met with Bukele (the president of El Salvador). In that meeting, he held that he couldn&#x27;t return the deported Venezuelans from El Salvador, because it&#x27;s up to El Salvador to do that. In the same interview, Bukele &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;_vluzonJnek?t=1223&quot;&gt;said&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that &lt;em&gt;he&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; couldn&#x27;t return them because he didn&#x27;t want to &quot;smuggle&quot; terrorists into the US. Let me say that again- the two men &lt;em&gt;responsible for this situation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; sat side by side in the same room, smirking, and &lt;em&gt;both&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; claimed that the deported Venezuelans couldn&#x27;t be returned to the US because the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; wouldn&#x27;t allow it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to summarize, Donald Trump is playing semantic games with old laws in order to justify sending people from the United States to a Salvadorean gulag with no due process, ignoring multiple court orders to do so. First to turn the planes around, and then to return specific individuals from El Salvador to the United States. His excuses for disregarding those court orders are constantly changing, but boil down to &quot;we can&#x27;t, &#x27;cause they&#x27;re in El Salvador now.&quot; Which, given our vast experience with &quot;police actions&quot;, &quot;peacekeeping efforts&quot;, and CIA-backed revolutions, is laughable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that same interview, Donald Trump &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;9gLrZ2EYzJw?t=58&quot;&gt;said&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that he would like to send &quot;homegrown&quot; criminals to El Salvador next. And I&#x27;m not betting he&#x27;s particularly interested in due process for them either.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;&#x27;It was a pretty dusty statute in 1917,&#x27; Professor Capozzola said, but its application was far-reaching, authorizing the detention of some 6,000 Germans&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;archive.is&#x2F;znWZt&quot;&gt;NYTimes&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;All told, more than 100,000 people of Japanese descent were forcibly interned in military facilities, gyms, jails, fair grounds and racetracks. Another 10,000 or so Germans and a few thousand Italians were also interned.&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;archive.is&#x2F;znWZt&quot;&gt;NYTimes&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Available on &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.whitehouse.gov&#x2F;presidential-actions&#x2F;2025&#x2F;03&#x2F;invocation-of-the-alien-enemies-act-regarding-the-invasion-of-the-united-states-by-tren-de-aragua&#x2F;&quot;&gt;whitehouse.gov&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and I&#x27;ve &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blackpath.blog&#x2F;data&#x2F;2025-03-15-alien-enemies-act&#x2F;&quot;&gt;archived&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; it locally in case it gets moved.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;archive.is&#x2F;O6ddQ&quot;&gt;this&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; NYT article, which has a timeline of events. I&#x27;m not sure what time zone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Published by &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cbsnews.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;venezuelans-deported-el-salvador-names&quot;&gt;CBS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and archived &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blackpath.blog&#x2F;data&#x2F;2025-3-15-deportations&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;6&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;...we could not find criminal records for 75% of the Venezuelans — 179 men — now sitting in prison.&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cbsnews.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;what-records-show-about-migrants-sent-to-salvadoran-prison-60-minutes-transcript&#x2F;&quot;&gt;CBS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;7&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;The United States is set to pay El Salvador $6 million to imprison 300 alleged members of the Venezuelan Tren de Aragua gang that it deports to the Central American country, for one year&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reuters.com&#x2F;world&#x2F;us&#x2F;us-pay-el-salvador-jail-300-alleged-gang-members-ap-reports-2025-03-15&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Reuters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Building A Better Watch</title>
		<published>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-05-01-the-toymaker/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-05-01-the-toymaker/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Johan sat uncomfortably across from Professor Malus, several notebooks resting on the wide desk between them. He had asked Malus to act as his advisor on the subject of his thesis for graduation, but now that he was sitting across from the older man, he didn’t know exactly what to expect. All of his notes, references, and tools sat on the near side of the desk, but one notebook had been pulled out, and Malus was reading from near the middle, with his brow furrowed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topic that Johan had selected was on the investigation of historical ritualism as a method used to buffer the side effects of manipulative magic. Ritualism was a practice with a long history in Ardglas and the surrounding area, but had mostly died out in the last few centuries. It was regarded as, at best, understandable superstition by ignorant savages, but Johan believed that it might have been a crude way to identify and avoid the side effects of manipulation. There was a fair amount of evidence that the practitioners of ritualism had been magic users of a sort, and some evidence that the ritual components were somehow associated with different parts of whatever system was being manipulated. To use the same example that Malus gave in his introductory course- healers drawing blood away from a wound might inadvertently starve surrounding tissues of the oxygen they needed to survive, killing flesh and organs. Ritualism, then, provided safeguards that either drew in additional blood from ‘upstream’, so to speak, or that would push back against the manipulation, if there were no other way to prevent damage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His notebooks included copious notes on both the historical record and more modern speculation (much of it his own) as well as dozens of diagrams and tables listing fragments of different rituals and speculating about their function. Johan was proud of the work he had put into his research, but his crowning achievement was sitting on the near side of the desk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was, for all intents and purposes, a perfectly normal pocket watch. The outside was made from some sort of cheap metal plated with pinchbeck (a type of imitation gold). Johan had bought a relatively cheap pocket watch from one of the many markets in Ardglas and then removed the mechanism to replace it with his own, made from corporeal magic. The gears and levers of the watch had been constructed laboriously over three months, by drawing from his own shallow well each day and carefully layering new magic over old, willing it into physical existence. The work had left him hungry, tired, and with almost no magic to use for anything else during that time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, on its own, wasn’t particularly noteworthy, except as a measure of his personal determination. What was novel about the watch was that, as far as Johan could tell, it would never run down, once wound. Or, rather, it might run down eventually (even in the safety of his own head, he was leery of making absolute claims) but likely not in the span of a lifetime.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;clockwork.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clockwork&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each gear was a very simple magical artifact that only did two things- maintained a passive connection to the balance wheel of the watch, and gathered energy from heat. The balance wheel drew on those reserves of energy to reinvest waste heat back into the movement of the watch, which made  the entire system almost perfectly contained.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had considered creating a watch crystal that would gather additional power from sunlight, but he hadn’t managed to find a way to make corporeal magic that was both transparent and capable of photosynthesis. It didn’t help that the total volume of the crystal was larger than any of the internal gears by several orders of magnitude, and the thought of spending an additional six months (at a minimum) tired, disgruntled, and powerless was just… unbearable. He hoped the demonstration of corporeal magic would be impressive, despite what he felt was something of a glaring flaw.
Malus set down the notebook with a sigh, and removed his glasses, rubbing his eyes for a moment. Johan realized that he was biting his nails and stopped just before the professor opened his eyes again and replaced his glasses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And you believe that ritualism can be harnessed to mitigate the negative effects of manipulation magic in general? That’s what all of this is gesturing toward?” Malus asked flatly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah- Yes. Corporeal magic could be used to create patterns that will mimic the rituals, and provide the same… buffering effect. Which would make manipulation magic more practical.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;If&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the rituals were actually an attempt to do what you describe, which there’s very little evidence for, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; corporeal mechanisms might be able to do the same, which &lt;em&gt;might&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; make manipulation more practical. There are a lot of leaps in that chain.” Malus reach forward and picked up the watch, turning it in his fingers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And this?” He asked, as he popped the cover open to inspect the ticking hands and the watch face.
“Ah- I’ve recreated each gear in the watch using corporeal magic, designed to gather waste heat and pass it to the balance wheel, which reinvests the energy into-” Johan began, but Malus cut him off.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Balance wheel?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A central component that rotates back and forth, driving the operation.” Johan answered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The balance wheel gathers the energy from the waste heat and reinvests it into the operation of the watch. The entire mechanism is essentially self-contained, and shouldn’t wind down for… well, I’m not sure exactly, but a very long time. Perhaps as long as fifty years.” Johan felt that he was being wildly conservative. Corporeal magic was nearly frictionless, if made correctly, and would produce much less waste heat than the original mechanism would have, even if one ignored the reclamation enchantment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Huh. And then…?” Malus asked, raising one eyebrow. “I imagine it would only need to be wound again to run for another fifty years?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes.” Johan said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Very clever… unique, I think.” He turned the watch thoughtfully on the table. “There are enchantments, magical items and so on that do similar things, but none that are so small and intricate, that I remember. Of course, most of those enchantments are concerned with effects much larger than keeping a watch running, but still.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not sure what the watch has to do with the research, if I’m being completely honest.” He glanced questioningly at Johan.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the rituals were large, clumsy attempts to buffer the side effects of manipulative magic, then I think that we could create a- ah -a focal pattern, is what I’ve been calling them- that would do the same. For example, imagine trying to heal a wound to the side of the head. Pushing blood from the wound back into the body might cause an aneurysm, or something like it, unless the wizard has an intimate knowledge of each vein and artery, and a way to model the blood pressure in the brain. A focal pattern connected to the subject would automatically manipulate the body to avoid this, and allow the wizard to push the blood while disregarding side effects.” Johan leaned forward excitedly as he spoke, his eyes focused on an image in his mind, rather than on his teacher.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The watch is a demonstration of just such a self-correcting mechanism- albeit without a connection to a subject or any way to control the operation.” He trailed off. The parallel seemed obvious, to him. “It’s a proof of concept, a way to show that a very simple magical artifact can automatically maintain a closed system.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hmm…” Malus stared at the watch in silence for a moment. Johan wondered if he was exploring the watch with his magical senses to verify the truth of what he had been told. There was no way to know, unless Johan were willing to extend his own magical senses into the watch as well. There were popular stories of wizards who had special vision to see other magic in the world, but the truth was that it was more like feeling your way around a dark room and bumping into other people doing the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a moment, Malus sat back in his chair with a thoughtful expression, looking out the window. The university was constructed in a large rectangle, though with many outbuildings and expansions that had been added at various times. In the center of the building was a large garden full of walking paths, benches, and a few small statues of important people (most of whom Johan had briefly investigated at one time or another, mainly to satisfy his own curiosity). Malus’ office bordered the garden, and large windows on one side of the room looked out over a row of bushes toward a walking path. Students were visible in the distance, walking from one classroom to another, sitting on the benches and reading or talking to each other. Malus stared in that direction, but his attention wasn’t on the students. He tapped his lips with two fingers and worked his chin forward and back as he thought.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This…” the professor began, gesturing toward the watch “… would make a fine thesis. It pushes the bounds of what we know of corporeal magic- few enchantments are this small, this intricate. Heat exchange isn’t entirely novel, but none operate at such a small scale. The craftsmanship is excellent.” Malus picked up the watch again, turning it in his fingers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And a closed system like this is… very interesting. I can imagine a dozen ways that this or similar items could be used to build valuable enchantments and there is a clear path to profitability with such machines, especially if you can find a manufacturer in the city to work with. It would reflect well on the school, and whoever you face in your thesis defense would be predisposed to accept your work, given that.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He set the watch down and leaned back in his chair, waving one hand toward the stack of notebooks and papers beside the watch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The research on ritual magic, however, is much less interesting. This idea has been investigated before, and nothing came of it. Have you read &lt;em&gt;Rituals, Then And Now&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johan knew the book. It began with a vague overview of a number of rituals from various time periods and regions, then tried to draw trite parallels between those rituals and the evils of modern society. It was one of a class of books that Johan mentally categorized as “motivated storytelling”- books that were less interested in providing information to the reader, and more interested in condemning some aspects of present-day culture with ritualism as a prop to support the idea that people had once been more noble, or thoughtful, or what-have-you in the past.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He despised the damn thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes, I did- it wasn’t particularly helpful. And it wasn’t what I would consider an ‘investigation’, really.” Johan said glumly, resisting the urge to rake his papers back into his arms and walk out of the room.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes, well. Taggart was an exceptional wizard- before his time. Setting that aside, many other wizards have investigated similar ideas, and the idea that ritualism was some form of rudimentary aid to casting is an old one. It’s never gone anywhere. As your advisor, I would be doing you a disservice if I suggested you continue with ritualism as a thesis topic, even with a unique angle like this fascinating little watch.” Malus turned the watch on the table again, smiling, but in a particularly soothing way that Johan found to be grating.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I understand this is a bit of a blow, but I think you’ll agree that delaying your graduation does no one any good, and once you have a position outside of the university, you’ll be free to follow whatever research catches your fancy.” He glanced at the clock hanging on the wall and then back to Johan, nodding his head in that direction. “I have twenty or thirty minutes if you would like to spend some time revising your approach and building a rough outline?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johan sighed and nodded. He hated being forced to reduce the scope of his work, but Malus wasn’t wrong. The entire situation was infuriating, however. And, if he was being honest with himself, he would have been more comfortable with the idea if the professor had seemed to share his frustration.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>A Practical Guide To Weaving</title>
		<published>2025-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-28-the-toymaker/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-28-the-toymaker/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Johan finished his diagram of the loom and inspected it with a critical eye. It was... mostly correct. He had never been much of an artist, but all the important bits were there, the lines were straight (or &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; straight, anyway), and the operation of the thing was clear. As clear as it could be, from a sketch. He had drawn multiple angles of the loom and labelled all of the components that seemed important, although most were labelled things like &quot;peddle&quot; and &quot;bundle of yarn.&quot; The only bit that he had an actual &lt;em&gt;name&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; for was the shuttle, and only because he had overheard the weaver ask one of her apprentices to fetch one. He could have just asked what all the different parts of the loom were called, but he was trying to stay out of everyone&#x27;s way, as best he could.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wizards were rarely interested in such mundane work, but Johan felt that was a mistake on their part, rather than an issue with the work itself. Magical experts were often inventive, but unfortunately, they were experts on &lt;em&gt;magic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. There were entire treasuries full of staffs that could summon fire, artifacts that could empower spells, or robes that kept one warm in the winter. All things that wizards, at one point or another, had created in order to make their lives easier. But there was a notable lack of magical looms. Johan suspected that it was partially due to the perception that weaving (or milling, or blacksmithing, or really &lt;em&gt;any&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; craft aside from magic and warfare) was low-class.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that perception, it was just &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. To make a magical loom, one had to know &lt;em&gt;how looms worked&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. This wasn&#x27;t an insurmountable difficulty. Johan had spent barely half a day sitting at the weavers shop, and he already had a good idea of their function. Although... there were likely nuances to the craft that he still wasn&#x27;t aware of. He absentmindedly underlined a note that read &quot;No Assumptions&quot; as he thought.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A magical sword, on the other hand? Trivial. Anyone could look at a sword and understand how it worked immediately. There was a handle on one end, a sharp edge, and a point on the other. No moving parts, and rarely more than two or three different materials. A skilled wizard could enchant them to be stay sharper, to resist wear, or even glow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although, now that Johan had visited a smithy, he thought there was likely more to creating a good sword than simply casting a spell to make it tougher. There was gradient of hardness through a blade- the edge needed to be hard in order to remain sharp, while the spine of the blade needed to be more flexible. He might be able to use manipulative magic to adjust whatever structure was in the metal so that the blade... hmm. He shuffled his papers, looking for his notes from the blacksmith.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Show me some magic?&quot; A high voice spoke at his elbow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johan jumped wildly, almost losing control of his papers, and whipped his head around toward the voice. It was a little boy, perhaps no more than four or five years old. The boy was blonde, skinny, and had dirt staining his face and knees of his britches. Despite the recent evidence that he had been playing in the dirt beside the shop, he looked very serious. Johan saw the weaver&#x27;s eyes widen from the corner of his eye, and she stopped working, holding the shuttle poised in one hand. He kept his gaze on the boy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wizards had a fearsome reputation, although it was (in Johan&#x27;s opinion) generally unearned. For the most part, they were fixated on various esoteric questions about magic, rather than on quests and battle. He had been in Dotton for a little over two weeks, and in all that time, no one had spoken to him except to respond to his questions. He straightened his papers and cleared his throat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;What sort of magic would you like to see...?&quot; He asked curiously.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Blow something up.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;That&#x27;s not... advisable. Everything here belongs to someone.&quot; Johan wasn&#x27;t overly comfortable with children, but he remembered how his father had spoken to &lt;em&gt;him&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as a child. Which was, now that he thought about it, almost exactly in the same way his father had spoken to everyone. Directly, clearly, and with endless patience for ignorance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Enchant my tunic!&quot; The boy responded, holding out the dirty cloth and looking down at it, then back to Johan.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Er...&quot; Johan cut his eyes sideways at the weaver for help, but she was now pretending to examine some thread. He sighed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Very well.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He laid one finger on the hem and reached into the well of magic inside his mind. It was like... he had seen a painting once, of a small, tentacled sea creature. It was said to be able to change the color of it&#x27;s skin and squeeze through absurdly small spaces. That was what he imagined his magic was like- a slim tentacle that could change color, shape, and length at will. He sent the tendril of magic into the cloth, tracing the threads and colors through the fabric. He made a few careful snips here and there, then began pulling the thread into a new configuration and splicing the cut ends back together. After a few false starts, he had the pattern in his mind, and the rest of the hem rearranged itself within a second or two. The edge of the boy&#x27;s tunic became an elaborate pattern of square knots that Johan had once seen on a dress in Ardglas.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each iteration of the pattern spiraled around itself, before doubling back enough to reach the starting point of the next, and small threads (mostly hidden on the underside of the fabric) hooked the corners of the spirals outward to force them into a square shape. There were no actual knots in the design, due to the limitations that he was working under, but it was prominent enough to be noticeable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He dislodged the dirt from the fabric, pushing it out to the surface and then allowing it to fall to the ground, before drawing his magic back into himself. He had lost roughly a fiftieth of his well in the operation (generating a few threads to replace those that were frayed), which was more than he would have liked. His magical abilities placed him at the extreme lower end of what was considered acceptable for a wizard, so much so that there had been some debate over his entrance to the university. It was a painful thought, but an old one, and he dismissed it easily. He had compensated for his relative weakness by becoming &lt;em&gt;very&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; good at manipulative magic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He inspected the hem closely, satisfied with his work. For a half remembered pattern, and on a task that he hadn&#x27;t attempted in years, a fiftieth of his well was fairly cheap.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he looked up, the weaver was standing in front of him with a conflicted look on her face. Johan released the tunic as the boy exclaimed over it, leaning back and clearing his throat uncomfortably. She knelt down and inspected the hem herself, keeping a wary eye on Johan as she did so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a moment, she looked back up and smiled politely.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Very pretty. How long will it last?&quot; She asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Well... it&#x27;s permanent. It&#x27;s not going to disappear tomorrow, or anything.&quot; Johan responded awkwardly. &quot;I just rearranged the thread.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the stories of wizards confused them with fairies and told of enchanted items or summoned gold disappearing at dawn. It was a common misconception. He considered explaining that wizards didn&#x27;t do that sort of thing (well, they &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; didn&#x27;t do that sort of thing), but thought better of it. Weirdly, the weaver reminded him of his mother, despite the two women looking nothing alike. Where his mother was a small, delicate woman, the weaver was almost as tall as he was, and broad through the shoulders. They had a similar polite confidence to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She nodded and fingered the hem again before letting it drop. The boy immediately ran away down the street, shouting for someone named &quot;Mac&quot; to come see his tunic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Well, it&#x27;s not really &lt;em&gt;permanent&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, then, but it&#x27;s very nice. You&#x27;ll have to fight the boys off with a stick now. They&#x27;ll all be wanting little things like that.&quot; She stood with her hands on her hips, staring after the screaming child.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;I&#x27;m Maeve.&quot; She said, looking back at him with a slow grin and extending her hand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Johan.&quot; He shook her hand shortly and stood up, collecting his papers. He wasn&#x27;t sure if he was leaving or not, but it seemed impolite to sit as she stood over him. She waited for him to gather his things, and then walked back toward where she had been working.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;What... uh, what do you mean? When you said &#x27;it&#x27;s not permanent&#x27;?&quot; He asked, trailing after her as she returned to the loom. She sat down before she replied, busying herself by straightening out the thread and rolling the excess up. After a brief silence, she finally sighed quietly, and handed him a scrap of cloth with a resigned air.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Here. Do it again.&quot; She said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat bemused, he laid his finger on the cloth and quickly rewove the threads into the same pattern. She turned it carefully, looking at the front and back before gesturing at him to lean in. She showed him the bottom of the fabric and ran her finger along the threads that pulled the square knots into shape.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;This? You&#x27;ve got threads hooked through the corners, holding the pattern in shape, but it&#x27;s only a few threads, here... and here. These will wear and break, eventually, &#x27;cause the clothing rubs against the legs and belt and so on. When it does, the pattern won&#x27;t be square anymore. It will be more of a... lumpy, round... thing.&quot; She turned the edge of the rag over, smoothing the pattern with two thumbs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Once the shape fails, these threads in the middle will be loose, and they&#x27;ll sag and make gaps in the fabric, see?&quot; She flexed the material, giving the edge some slack, and Johan saw small openings. &quot;You&#x27;ve, I think, rearranged the threads in the cloth, and picked out the stitching that ran along the edge of his tunic. These threads aren&#x27;t running straight anymore, they&#x27;re hooked around in different directions to make the spiral. Once the threads in the back fail, the edge will fray very quickly.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She released the tension on the cloth, and it relaxed back into the square pattern that Johan had made. He stood silently, frustrated at himself. He should have realized that the hem was intended to keep the edge of the cloth from fraying, but it hadn&#x27;t occurred to him. She was right, though, he saw immediately. She would have to repair the tunic or at least restitch the pattern in a matter of weeks, likely.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johan&#x27;s mother still wore a dress with a very similar scrollwork pattern that he had created for her as a student. She joked that it was &quot;thematically appropriate&quot; for her job as a bookkeeper. His face flushed as he wondered how much time she had spent, painstakingly picking apart that pattern and then restitching it, to make it last.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;It&#x27;s very pretty though.&quot; Maeve said soothingly, patting his arm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Small Magic</title>
		<published>2025-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-26-the-toymaker/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-26-the-toymaker/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Professor Malus walked back and forth, moving his hands as he spoke. The class room was shaped like a wide funnel, with the professor’s podium positioned on the stage at the bottom, and rows of higher seats circling the stage. The ranks of students around him listened intently, occasionally making notes or (in some cases) furiously copying everything that he had written on the chalkboard into their own notebooks. A few seated in the back gave every appearance of ignoring the lecture entirely. Johan sat in the lowest row, dead center. Not because it was the position that he wanted to be in, but because he knew that it would probably give him an easy 2-5% bump in his grade.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years ago, a teacher had shown Johan collected statistics for every student in his class, going back a decade or more. All other things being equal, students in the front row had average grades four points higher than those who sat in the back. Part of this, Johan guessed, was because the teacher knew their faces and would be more motivated to help them, part of it was probably that they were more likely to ask for help (sitting in close proximity gave a feeling of intimacy, whether it was real or not), but the largest part was just that it was hard to completely ignore someone who was speaking loudly only a few feet away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Magic is fixed at &lt;em&gt;formation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;-” the theoretical point during pregnancy at which a fetus became a human being “- and there is no way to get more of it. It cannot be taken away, only restrained or controlled. You’ve heard, I’m sure, of the many schools and varieties of magic. Many of you already have a specialization, or plans on a specialization. For our purposes-” Professor Malus walked back to the chalkboard and picked up the chalk from where he had left it on a small table against the wall, ignoring the cloud of powder that he brushed from the table as he did. “-there are only two types of magic. &lt;em&gt;Generative&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;manipulative&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Generative magic, also sometimes called ‘simple’ magic-” he turned and raised an eyebrow at the class.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“-which you will find to be a misleading label, I’m sure. Generative magic is the process of creating something from &lt;em&gt;raw magic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. A wizard who consumes their own magic to create a flame is using generative magic. Creation of water &lt;em&gt;ex nihilo&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is generative. It may surprise you to learn that levitation, in most cases, is also generative. Generative magic is called ‘simple’ because in many ways, it is. The wizard is expending their limited supply of magic to create some change in the world.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The professor had a habit, borne from long years teaching, of stressing key words as he spoke. He moved from side to side, building up a list of examples for generative magic, then noting down authors, dates and titles to the side- reference material that would be helpful for the test. Which, Johan realized, as he glanced down at his notes and schedule, was only a few weeks away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In contrast, &lt;em&gt;manipulative&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; magic involves the control of natural forces without expenditure. It requires an intimate knowledge of the forces being manipulated. A…” Malus hesitated for the first time, as if he were unsure what example to use ”… healer may draw blood away from a wound, using only the natural ability of &lt;em&gt;extruded magic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to nudge and pull the blood. An experienced wizard may be able to use that same ability to control the outcome of a coin flip. At the extreme, magic may be used to permanently &lt;em&gt;alter&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a human body, granting increased strength, speed, and durability-” he broke off as a student raised her hand “-yes?”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s something that specialists in body magic can do, right?” She asked, somewhat hesitantly, now that so many eyes were on her.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Exactly! Yes. That is the primary skill that body magi pursue. The drawback of the technique is the time required. Each body specialist will spend decades gradually improving their body while avoiding or undoing the detrimental side effects of their changes as they do. Every part of the body is connected to every other part -a &#x27;world in a bottle&#x27; as Spencer says in &lt;em&gt;A Century of Growth&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Changing any part can have catastrophic effects on the others.” He clasped his hands behind his back, walking slowly forward to the front row of seats and scanning the audience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Manipulative magic is capable of producing permanent effects on the world, without the &lt;em&gt;expenditure&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, however temporarily, of magic. For that reason, it has attracted much interest in the past. But generative magic, for all it’s limitations on that front, is fundamentally &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. To quote another great wizard- &#x27;if you have a nail and a hammer, just &lt;em&gt;hit the damn nail&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scattered laughter rippled around the classroom at that. Malus smiled faintly and paused for a moment for it to fade away. After it did, he reminded everyone to complete the latest essay, due Monday, and began stacking his books and gathering his things.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Trump Wants A Third Term</title>
		<published>2025-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-25-trump-third-term/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-25-trump-third-term/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;eric_trump_2028.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Eric Trump wearing a &amp;#x27;Trump 2028&amp;#x27; hat&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;It was nice of his dad to let him wear the merchandise.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the first time I heard Donald Trump joke about wanting a third term, I took it seriously. I took it seriously, because I&#x27;ve had experience with people like him. They float terrible ideas and then say &quot;it&#x27;s a &lt;em&gt;joke&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. You&#x27;re so &lt;em&gt;thin skinned&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Geez.&quot; But if they really like the idea they&#x27;ll come back to it again and again, trying to find some angle to make it happen. The side effect of this is that it begins to sound less shocking and infuriating every time you hear it. They wear you down. They badger you. Eventually, it might even seem reasonable&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This is what Trump is doing with the idea of a third term.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, claiming that his idle speculation about running for a third term is a &lt;em&gt;joke&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; allows his supporters to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;ubo2GnEnpwo?t=305&quot;&gt;join in&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. As more and more of his supporters vocally support the idea (mainly as a way to needle liberals), their support gives it a veneer of respectability for all the people who &lt;em&gt;aren&#x27;t&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in on the joke.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, crowds of people are chanting &quot;twelve more years&quot; at his rallies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People see these chanting crowds and begin to believe that there is poltical &lt;em&gt;will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; behind the idea. They came to the party late, and didn&#x27;t see the winks and smirks. As more serious support begins to materialize, those who were in on the joke either become serious or leave, and you end up with an actual movement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why revolutionaries always try to capture radio and television stations, and then broadcast messages claiming &lt;em&gt;that they&#x27;ve already won&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. This is why political candidates &lt;em&gt;always claim their victory is assured&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Because the appearance of inevitability and public support draws more supporters, and if you can project that illusion convincingly enough (say, by having crowds chant on national television as a joke), you can create a movement from &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I don&#x27;t believe that Donald Trump has a master plan to gather support for a third term, I think practically, that&#x27;s what he&#x27;s doing. He does this intuitively, out of long habit. He says whatever he wants, and says it with a smile or an innocent expression, and then decides which things are jokes and which aren&#x27;t after the fact. When you take that behavior and project it out over six years, you end up with something that looks, if you squint just right, like a long-running plot to normalize a third term.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;jan_6_attack_on_capital.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Trump supporters mob the capital on Janurary 6th, 2021&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Normalize it enough, and your supporters might even attack their own capital for you.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve had more than one conversation with conservatives who believe this is all still a joke. I&#x27;m not sure how to reply to that. Yeah, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. And the moment Donald Trump thinks he has enough support, it will &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; being a joke.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, the Trump store has started selling merchandise with slogans like &quot;Trump 2028&quot; and &quot;Rewrite the Rules&quot;. In the wake of that, I wanted to pull together all of the times Trump has joked about a third term to make it clear that this isn&#x27;t, and has never been, some idle thought. He has been rolling this idea around in his mind and trying to get other people on board since half way through his &lt;em&gt;first&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; term.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the end of his second term approaches, I think he will try to turn this from a joke into a serious effort, and when he does, I want a record of everything that led up to it. I&#x27;ll be updating this timeline with new quotes and events as they happen. If anyone reading this notices one that I missed or a mistake in the dates or sources, feel free to send me an email.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2016&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note &quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2016-11-08&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&amp;#x2F;wiki&amp;#x2F;2016_United_States_presidential_election&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            Donald Trump wins the presidential election
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2017&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2018&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2018-03-03&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.cnn.com&amp;#x2F;2018&amp;#x2F;03&amp;#x2F;03&amp;#x2F;politics&amp;#x2F;trump-maralago-remarks&amp;#x2F;index.html&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;[Xi Jinping] is now president for life. President for life. No, he’s great [...] I think it’s great. Maybe we’ll have to give that a shot some day.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2018-04&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.cnn.com&amp;#x2F;2019&amp;#x2F;06&amp;#x2F;18&amp;#x2F;politics&amp;#x2F;donald-trump-term-limit&amp;#x2F;index.html&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;We’re cutting record numbers of regulations – we’ve cut more regulations in a year and a quarter than any administration whether it’s four years, eight years, or in one case 16 years [...] Should we go back to 16 years? Should we do that? Congressman, can we do that?&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2018-04&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.cnn.com&amp;#x2F;2019&amp;#x2F;06&amp;#x2F;18&amp;#x2F;politics&amp;#x2F;donald-trump-term-limit&amp;#x2F;index.html&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;You know the last time I jokingly said that the papers start saying, ‘He’s got despotic tendencies,’ [...] I’m not looking to do it. Unless you want to do it, that’s OK.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2019&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2019-04-18&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.washingtonpost.com&amp;#x2F;politics&amp;#x2F;trump-again-jokes-about-staying-on-as-president-for-more-than-two-terms&amp;#x2F;2019&amp;#x2F;04&amp;#x2F;18&amp;#x2F;05a5afce-6207-11e9-9ff2-abc984dc9eec_story.html&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;I was going to joke, General, and say at least for 10 or 14 years, but we would cause bedlam if I said that, so we’ll say six.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2019-09-26&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.bloomberg.com&amp;#x2F;news&amp;#x2F;videos&amp;#x2F;2019-09-27&amp;#x2F;trump-jokes-about-third-term-in-closed-door-remarks-video-shows-video&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;[...] looking good for another four years, and then if we want to another four.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2019-12-07&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;slate.com&amp;#x2F;news-and-politics&amp;#x2F;2020&amp;#x2F;02&amp;#x2F;trump-jokes-rigged-elections-chaos.html&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;One of them said, &amp;#x27;You know he’s going to win, don’t you? And you know, at the end of his second term, you know he’s not leaving. He’s not leaving. You know that.&amp;#x27; And I thought he’s a comedian. I thought he was kidding. He’s for real. So now we have to start thinking about that, because it’s not a bad idea.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2020&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2020-09-12&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.cbsnews.com&amp;#x2F;news&amp;#x2F;what-trump-has-said-about-pursuing-a-third-term&amp;#x2F;&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;We&amp;#x27;re going to win four more years in the White House. And then after that, we&amp;#x27;ll negotiate, right? [...] we&amp;#x27;re probably entitled to another four after that.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2020-09-14&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.youtube.com&amp;#x2F;watch?v=pzvfVB4GqC8&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;And after we win four more years, we&amp;#x27;ll ask for maybe another four or so.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2021&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2022&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2023&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2024&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2024-05-18&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.politico.com&amp;#x2F;news&amp;#x2F;2024&amp;#x2F;05&amp;#x2F;18&amp;#x2F;trump-at-nra-convention-floats-a-three-term-presidency-00158786&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;You know, FDR 16 years — almost 16 years — he was four terms. I don’t know, are we going to be considered three-term? Or two-term?&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2024-11-14&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.youtube.com&amp;#x2F;watch?v=QiHURe7WVjo&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;I suspect I won’t be running again, unless you do something. Unless you say, &amp;#x27;He&amp;#x27;s so good, we just have to figure it out&amp;#x27;.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;dateitem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;2025&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;


    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note &quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-01-23&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.congress.gov&amp;#x2F;bill&amp;#x2F;119th-congress&amp;#x2F;house-joint-resolution&amp;#x2F;29&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            Representative Ogles proposes amendment to the constitution that would allow Donald Trump to serve a third term
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-01-25&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.youtube.com&amp;#x2F;watch?v=OXo-XBvMAUQ&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;It will be the greatest honor of my life to serve, not once but twice — or three times or four times [...] no, it will be to serve twice.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note &quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-01-26&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.whois.com&amp;#x2F;whois&amp;#x2F;thirdtermproject.com&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            The domain thirdtermproject.com is purchased.
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-01-27&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;youtu.be&amp;#x2F;x6yJB5MVIEE?t=580&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;I think I&amp;#x27;m not allowed to run again. I&amp;#x27;m not sure. Am I allowed to run again?&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note &quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-02-19&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.youtube.com&amp;#x2F;watch?v=3ErXtixyCc0&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            The Third Term Project displays banners and merchandise at CPAC
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-02-20&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;youtu.be&amp;#x2F;Vw2AZK5gEok?t=825&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;Should I run again? You tell me.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-03-30&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.nbcnews.com&amp;#x2F;politics&amp;#x2F;donald-trump&amp;#x2F;trump-third-term-white-house-methods-rcna198752&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;A lot of people want me to do it [...] There are methods which you could do it. [...] I&amp;#x27;m not joking.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-04-01&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.youtube.com&amp;#x2F;watch?v=Pl6Eawz5bhQ&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;There&amp;#x27;s a whole story about running for a third term. I don&amp;#x27;t know. I never looked into it. They do say there&amp;#x27;s a way you can do it.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note &quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-04-24&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.politico.com&amp;#x2F;news&amp;#x2F;2025&amp;#x2F;04&amp;#x2F;24&amp;#x2F;trump-organization-2028-campaign-hats-00308024&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            Trump store begins selling merchandise that says &amp;quot;Trump 2028&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Rewrite the Rules&amp;quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-05-04&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.nbcnews.com&amp;#x2F;politics&amp;#x2F;trump-administration&amp;#x2F;read-full-transcript-president-donald-trump-interviewed-meet-press-mod-rcna203514&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;I will say this. So many people want me to do it. I have never had requests so strong as that. But it’s something that, to the best of my knowledge, you’re not allowed to do. I don’t know if that’s constitutional that they’re not allowing you to do it or anything else. But, there are many people selling the 2028 hat. But this is not something I’m looking to do.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;entry&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator &quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&quot;note darken&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;2025-05-13&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.msnbc.com&amp;#x2F;rachel-maddow-show&amp;#x2F;maddowblog&amp;#x2F;remarks-us-troops-trump-renews-talk-third-term-constitution-rcna207236&quot; class=&quot;link&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;body&quot;&gt;
            &quot;As you know we won three elections. And some people want us to do a fourth. I don&amp;#x27;t know. I&amp;#x27;ll have to think about that. You saw the new hat?… It says Trump 2028.&quot;
        &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;source&quot;&gt;
            - Donald Trump
        &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;markeritem&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;indicator&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;label&quot;&gt;YOU ARE HERE&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;In a 2015 study, researchers discovered that familiarity can overpower rationality and that repetitively hearing that a certain statement is wrong can paradoxically cause it to feel right.&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Illusory_truth_effect&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>How To Steal A Road</title>
		<published>2025-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-24-the-toymaker/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-24-the-toymaker/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dotton was a backwater. It was a small village surrounded by rolling hills, rocky fields, and crooked forests, backed up against a mountain range to the northwestern edge of the continent. Beyond the mountains were sheer cliffs running down to a dangerous and unpredictable coastline where nothing of importance could be found. There were no great trading routes, no strategic features that an enemy might want to secure, no great wealth of knowledge. The King knew this, his advisors knew this, the lords and ladies surrounding the royal court (if they had ever heard of Dotton at all) knew this, and the residents of Dotton knew this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They didn&#x27;t mind at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Villages with valuable mines were plundered, and cities with great libraries and ancient wisdom were sometimes burned to the ground for heresy of one sort or another. Centers of trade were the first place invading armies went, and any village on a line between the border and capital was a likely target for sacking and pillage. Bad business, the old men of Dotton agreed, as they leaned back in their chairs in front of the local store with their pipes. Not anything a fine, hardworking Dotton man should get tangled up in. They blew smoke rings into the evening air and watched children chase each other through the muddy streets, dodging wagons full of grain and washerwomen carrying their bundles.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dotton had one feature that even a larger city might envy. They had a road. Several centuries earlier, the great-great-great-great-grandfather of the current King Withelm had declared that all cities, great or small, would be connected to the capital by a road. But first, an advisor had pointed out, it was necessary to know what constituted a &quot;city&quot; and what made a city different from a village, or a town. Or even a logging camp. It would be an overwhelming task to build a highway to every collection of shacks in the kingdom. After much discussion, the King and his advisors had decided that the main feature separating a city from a village was the number of people who lived there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The King, with only a bit of throat clearing, made a slightly less resonent proclamation that all cities, villages, and towns would participate in a general census to determine which areas would be connected to the capital.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On hearing this, the elders of Dotton ruminated on the matter. It would be a great boon to Dotton, they agreed, if the town had a real road to the capital. Easier to sell their goods to cities in between, easier to receive help during famine or after the great storms that sometimes devastated the area. They read the announcement to each other again, mulling over the number of citizens that determined whether a village was a &lt;em&gt;village&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;town&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, or a &lt;em&gt;city&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. None of them knew how many people lived in and around Dotton, but it certainly wasn&#x27;t enough to warrant a highway.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dotton had a mayor, and while the old folk gave great weight to their own discussions, they had no true power or influence and were generally ignored by everyone else. With one exception. A boy of fifteen, the weaver&#x27;s apprentice, had walked away from the messenger and the grumbling cluster of old folk, thinking about the message himself. He agreed with their assessment. Dotton &lt;em&gt;could&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; use a highway.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six months later, the census taker arrived to a very different village. Every street corner was crowded with boys and girls, their sisters and brothers, their cousins, concerned aunties, nephews, and uncles. The census man commandeered the main room of a local inn, and requested that all of the citizens of the village present themselves, which they were only too happy to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first person to do so was a smiling boy of fifteen, who presented the man with a pie as a welcoming gift.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man &lt;em&gt;may&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; have noticed that some of the people who presented themselves to be counted were suspiciously youthful, despite claiming to be of age. He &lt;em&gt;may&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; have noticed that some of those who came in on the second day looked suspiciously similar to those who had presented themselves on the first. He might, if he were the inquisitive sort, have wondered why the boy who had given him pie stood against the outside wall of the inn, organizing and managing the line that often stretched down the street.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it was a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; good pie.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the elders of Dotton received word that the village had been declared a city, they nodded to each other and stroked their beards. A lot of folk living out in these woods, they said. Perhaps Dotton wasn&#x27;t a city like the capital, with everyone crammed together in tight little streets and hemmed in by walls, but there were a lot of people out in the forest. Not &lt;em&gt;traditional&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; folk, maybe, but good people all the same. Why, the streets were positively overflowing when the census man had come.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them eyed the whistling boy who was cheerfully repairing a loom nearby. Too clever for his own good, they grumbled to each other. But they grumbled quietly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the road was completed. It ran from Dotton and through a number of other villages, towns, and hamlets, eventually merging with other great highways and smaller lanes before reaching the great gates of Ardglas, the capital. Each village and town along the new road was pleased to find themselves connected to their neighbors in the northwest and southeast, but there was a distinct lack of surprise among the people. Many had been visited by a young man from Dotton well before the census man had arrived, and taken impromptue holidays during the census itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Families whose children had grown, married, and moved to neighboring towns were now able to visit each other. Packages, goods, and even letters could be sent easily up and down the highway, and while the price of wool (Dotton&#x27;s primary export) lowered somewhat in towns closer to the capital, the increased quantity that they sold more than made up for it. All in all, everyone agreed, the road was a vast improvement over the various muddy tracks and trails that had previous connected each town to its neighbors.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mayor of Dotton eventually told his wife about the odd visit he had received from the weaver&#x27;s boy, who had asked many insightful questions about how roads were planned and constructed. Civic planning and trade were subjects that the mayor thoroughly enjoyed, and they had spent a pleasant afternoon pouring over the maps in the mayor&#x27;s office.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone noticed that on all subsequent censuses Dotton was registered as a village rather than a city, they kept it to themselves. Over the the next century, invaders attacked and were repelled, bandits destroyed bridges, cities were sometimes sacked or abandoned. The roads, which were never entirely finished in the first place, began to fall into disrepair. Dotton had no great wealth to attract bandits, no borders with aggressive neighbors, and no cities to sack. Within two generations, only a handful of the great roads were still intact, and the road between Dotton and Ardglas was one of them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story about a clever Dotton boy who had swindled a king was well known in Dotton and the surrounding area. Lively arguments sometimes still broke out, with different families claiming him as an ancestor. Most of these claims were based on half-remembered family trees or the presumed infidelity of someones great-great-great-great-grandparent. In the end, though, it was not much more than a historical footnote.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a wizard came to town.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Eating Meat Is Morally Indefensible</title>
		<published>2025-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-23-vegetarianism/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-23-vegetarianism/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;abed_tries_to_fix_the_pencil_1.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Abed tries to fix the pencil&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Trying to fix a pencil named Steve&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has moral intuitions. They (probably) come from some combination of our biology, environment, culture, and personal reasoning. Moral philosophy&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; is the practice of comparing those intuitions to each other to tease out contradictions and inconsistencies. Once you&#x27;ve done this, you can discard or adjust some of your positions to reduce the inconsistency. The goal is to create a moral framework that is as simple as it can be, but no simpler&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not a moral philosopher in any possible sense, but I think that the practice I&#x27;ve just described should be done by everyone. We all have a patchwork of moral beliefs, some inherited from parents, some picked up from friends or the media. Teasing out the inconsistencies helps us clarify what is most important to us&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, and allows us to discard beliefs that contradict other, more deeply held convictions. Having a flexible, battle tested, and simple moral framework allows us to make good decisions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have observed that when I think about bad things happening to people a long way away, I generally don&#x27;t feel much. I know that children being murdered in a different country is just as &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as children being murdered in my neighborhood, because I can&#x27;t see any way that distance would change the degree of badness. It just doesn&#x27;t hit me emotionally as much as it should. It&#x27;s not that I &lt;em&gt;couldn&#x27;t&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; get emotional about it- I could. I could watch videos about it, think about it a lot, and I&#x27;m sure that eventually I&#x27;d have an emotional reaction to it. It&#x27;s just a lot more work than if the murders were happening nearby. I think emotions are unreliable indicators of whether something is morally wrong or not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;em&gt;moral intuition&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, on the other hand, comes to the same conclusion whether the children are close or distant. It&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;very wrong&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. There are unlikely edge cases where killing one child saves some number of others, but the base case is that it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;very wrong&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If other people are like me, then we all have a fundamental insensitivity to scope&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Large numbers, great distances, vast stretches of time. We can&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; grasp these things. We can&#x27;t give people on the other side of those great distances the empathy that they deserve. We can&#x27;t grasp that a million deaths is one million times more tragic than a single death. It doesn&#x27;t kick us in the gut the way someone dying next to us does. But, in an interesting twist, we&#x27;ve figured out a way to work around that, if we want to. In the immortal words of Jeff, from the show Community-&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can pick up this pencil, tell you it&#x27;s name is &quot;Steve&quot;, and go like this [breaks the pencil], and part of you &lt;em&gt;dies&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
-- &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;z906aLyP5fg?si=toU8Hr22nE-t19AJ&quot;&gt;Jeff&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason we can do this is because we&#x27;re imaginative. We&#x27;ve adapted to our scope insensitivity by learning to &lt;em&gt;imagine&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; what other people might be going through. We take it &lt;em&gt;personally&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Sometimes the thing we&#x27;re sympathizing with isn&#x27;t even alive. This is mostly great! We have this innate flaw that makes it difficult for us to give events the moral weight that they deserve, and we&#x27;ve managed to fix it (sort of) by using another innate feature of humanity- imagination. But in another way, it&#x27;s not, because we can &lt;em&gt;turn it off&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have some motivation to disregard a thousand deaths on the other side of the planet, it&#x27;s startlingly easy to just stop feeling bad about it. Motivated reasoning is a hell of a drug&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. All of a sudden, the situation becomes &lt;em&gt;complicated&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. There are other considerations. Maybe they brought it on themselves through some chain of actions, and so you&#x27;re not obligated to feel bad about their suffering or the suffering of their families. Maybe someone from their ethnic group committed some atrocity, so you don&#x27;t have to care about them. Sure, if someone else brings it up, you&#x27;ll &lt;em&gt;say&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; you do- of course you care. In a technical way. The same way I can &lt;em&gt;say&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that a million deaths is roughly one million times as tragic as one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&#x27;m not putting forth the effort to &lt;em&gt;give a damn&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; about them in the same way those students gave a damn about a pencil named &quot;Steve&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter? What the hell does this have to do with vegetarianism? It matters because I think that animals have moral weight. And I think most people agree with me. If I were walking down the street, and I caught sight of a guy in an alleyway breaking a rock with a hammer, I would... probably wonder why he was doing that. If I were walking down the street and saw a guy in an alleyway beating a &lt;em&gt;dog&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with a hammer, I would immediately try to stop him, probably by pulling him away or shouting at him. If I saw a guy beating a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with a hammer, I wouldn&#x27;t bother shouting- I&#x27;d just club him from behind immediately. It feels like two of these situations are morally relevant, and one isn&#x27;t. But you see the spectrum here: rocks &amp;lt; animals &amp;lt; people.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If animals have moral weight, then their suffering and death is &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Maybe not quite as wrong as an equivalent number of people suffering and dying, but wrong all the same. So far this year, the United States has slaughtered 17 billion animals. If it&#x27;s wrong to harm and kill animals, then harming and killing &lt;em&gt;17 billion&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of them&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;6&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; is roughly 17 billion times as wrong. And any amount of moral weight at all, when multiplied by 17 billion, is &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t feel a thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If killing one animal is wrong and we&#x27;re killing 17 billion of them and I &lt;em&gt;don&#x27;t care&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, then it&#x27;s probably because I&#x27;m not reacting appropriately to the scope of what is happening. So what would I do if I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; feel the appropriate amount of horror at that knowledge? Well, I&#x27;d do whatever I could to stop it. I could bomb slaughter houses. I could protest. I could do all sorts of things, and many of them would lead to jail time or at least seriously impact my ability to keep a job and provide for my family. At the very least, the &lt;em&gt;very least&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, I could refuse to participate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when I say that it&#x27;s the least I could do, I really mean it. It didn&#x27;t require any difficult decisions. I&#x27;m not struggling to feed myself in a wilderness. I&#x27;m not scrabbling for every bit of energy I can get. I&#x27;m a reasonably well-paid professional in the richest country that has ever existed. I can eat out whenever I want, and there is almost always non-meat food that I can eat- more than there has ever been before, actually.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question is, do I enjoy a &lt;em&gt;few more&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; kinds of food, and participate in a widespread immoral practice, or accept a mild inconvenience in the hope that my trivial rejection of that practice leads to less death?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was, and remains, a simple decision for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal definition. I&#x27;m not formally educated in any of this, and I&#x27;m taking what seems useful and discarding everything that seems pedantic or pointless.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the internet has taught me to be suspicious of quotes from Einstein, the saying &quot;everything should be as simple as it can be, but no simpler&quot; was probably a somewhat wittier phrasing of something he actually did say.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;To crush your enemies, to see them driven before you, and to hear the lamentation of their women&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=_XUu3_pLPUE&quot;&gt;Conan The Barbarian&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;...scope insensitivity is a cognitive bias that occurs when the valuation of a problem is not valued with a multiplicative relationship to its size&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Scope_neglect&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Individuals tend to favor evidence that coincides with their current beliefs and reject new information that contradicts them, despite contrary evidence&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Motivated_reasoning&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;6&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;animalclock.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; keeps track of the numbers, based (I think) on USDA statistics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>A Wizard Comes To Town</title>
		<published>2025-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-22-the-toymaker/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-22-the-toymaker/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gage had never met a wizard before. Most people who lived in Dotton and the farmland that surrounded the small village hadn&#x27;t, so it was no surprise that Gage, being one of those people, hadn&#x27;t either. Wizards were solitary creatures, often compared to dragons- powerful, reclusive, and mysterious. Unlike dragons, they generally had a firm relationship with the King through their various schools and trade organizations. The kingdom sometimes called on them for services, but for the most part, their power, and the power of their guild, kept them independent. Gage, despite having never met an actual wizard before, &lt;em&gt;had&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; heard any number of stories. Wizards in their wrath, laying waste to cities. Wizards providing valuable but indirect support to young fools with magical swords. Wizards defending kingdoms, or going bad and being defended against.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the stories had prepared him for the silent young man who was now sitting against the wall just inside the entrance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boy had been waiting for him at the crack of dawn, standing patiently in the mud outside of Gage&#x27;s shop with a signed document from the local mayor. The document requested, in the polite but firm language of the law, that the bearer be allowed to observe any and all manufacturing work conducted in the city, provided he didn&#x27;t get in the way. Gage had grudgingly let him in and brusquely ordered him to stay out of harms way. Privately, he had expected an endless stream of questions and all sorts of other nosey-ness, but the kid had simple posted himself by the door, taken out a sheaf of papers, and begun to write. He occasionally looked up from his notes and stared around as Gage laid out his hammers, lit the forge, and brought out some bar stock.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he prepared his workspace, Gage mulled the situation over. The document had refered to the boy as &quot;Johan Scrivener, Wizard.&quot; Unless the kid was a lot more ballsy than he seemed, it was unlikely that he had somehow stabbed a wizard in a dark alleyway and stolen the papers, and if he &lt;em&gt;had&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, he would likely be touring other shops with more valuable goods. There were a lot of threats in the blacksmithing trade, but few of them involved theft. First, because all of the merchandise was heavy as hell, and second, because robbing a man twice your size who collects weapons and hammers was a great way to find an early grave. No, the boy (Gage couldn&#x27;t bring himself to think of a lad barely twenty years old as anything but a boy, wizard or no) was probably an actual, honest-to-gods wizard. The thought was uncomfortable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gage squinted at a note, scribbled on a scrap of paper that had been reused so many times that it was more gray than cream. An order for a short knife from a local, half-a-dozen hinges... he lifted the scrap and looked at the back, then the front again. He could have sworn there was more. Drawers opened and slammed as he rummaged through the various mismatched nooks and crannies on the lopsided desk, until he found another scrap of paper, even darker. Ah-hah. Twenty fittings for harnesses of various types, and a plow. The plow was going to take more than a day to finish off, and he was in no hurry. He dropped the second scrap on top of the first, then shoved both of them into the corner as he dug through the rest of the clutter for an apron.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the chaotic desk, the actual workspace of the forge was remarkably clean. Gage had learned his trade from his father, who had smacked him more than once for leaving the forge a mess. Eventually, he had absorbed the rough lessons. The shop was swept every night. The tools were cleaned and oiled every day. The stock was carefully accounted for. A messy shop would quickly lead to sloppy work. He whistled as he selected a hammer and held his hand to the forge, testing the heat. Eventually, his worthless apprentice would arrive and work the bellows, but until then, it was no great effort to press the handle himself, stirring the fire with each movement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He worked steadily for the next several hours, heating and hammering the steel for the short knife before quenching, reheating, and setting the piece aside, moving on to the hinges. They were finicky, but it wasn&#x27;t particularly difficult to roll the edges of the iron around a rod of harder steel. It was mindless, almost. He remembered the first time he had tried to make a simple hinge, the frustration he had felt as what should have been a smooth curve had come out lopsided again and again. And again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He snorted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years of practice had taught him a few things, he figured. As an apprentice, he had concentrated intensely, tapping, adjusting, and tapping some more. All that tense effort, for a lopsided and dented hinge. These days he could do it with his eyes closed, almost. Two strikes, turn, two strikes, done. Another perfect hinge dropped onto the small pile, and he straightened, rubbing one fist into his back.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime during the work, his apprentice, Rog, had appeared and taken over the bellows, glancing uncertainly at the wizard sitting calmly by the door. Gage glanced at them both, then caught Rog&#x27;s eye and shrugged. He turned back to the forge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work continued through the day and into the afternoon. Gage steadily worked his way through the fittings, keeping one eye on his apprentice as the boy labored, first over the bellows, and then at the second anvil over a much smaller pile of fixtures. He would likely give a discount to the customers who received Rog&#x27;s work. They were certainly uglier, but the kid needed practice working on things that were actually going to be used. Gage had heard of other masters setting their apprentices to building puzzles or other useless shapes to teach particular techniques, but he didn&#x27;t approve of this. There was more to the craft than simply knowing the tools: there was a pride in seeing your work being used by your neighbors. A good smith needed to know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; his work was used. Without the &lt;em&gt;how&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, the fastenings themselves were just shapes made from iron or steel. If you had the &lt;em&gt;how&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, then sometimes it was possible to make better fastenings, better hinges.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, Gage straightened once more and turned to drop the last fitting on the bench, only to come face-to-face with the young wizard.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He almost jerked back in alarm, but managed to control the impulse, barely. They stood like that, in the heat, as Rog continued to hammer behind him, oblivious. Gage was sweating heavily, both from the labor and the nearby forge, but the wizard... wasn&#x27;t. His gaze was just as cool, and for the first time, Gage noticed that his eyes were an icy blue. That didn&#x27;t seem right. Gage could have sworn they were brown, when the kid had first approached him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Yeah?&quot; He asked roughly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Why did you quench and reheat the hinges entirely, but only quenched the edge of the blade?&quot; Johan replied, his eyes on the pile of hinges.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gage glanced down at the smoking pile of iron, confused, and then back up at the boy, who held his papers and short pen expectantly. He noticed, abruptly, that the inkwell for the pen was a clever little tube attached to the wizards belt. The cap had a neat hole in the middle, allowing the pen to dip in, but keeping the majority of the ink from spilling out. Copper, if he wasn&#x27;t mistaken.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;The quenching hardens the steel, an&#x27; heating softens it. Quenching the hinges makes them hard, and reheating takes some of that away. They need to be hard so they don&#x27;t bend under the weight of a door, but too hard an&#x27; they&#x27;ll crack. The knife needs a hard edge for sharpening, but a flexible spine, so it don&#x27;t shatter.&quot; He answered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rog had finally noticed their conversation and set his work aside, drifting closer as he pretended to wipe his tools down and return them to their positions on the nearby workbench. Gage could almost see the boy&#x27;s ears twitching as he listened.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johan nodded and made a few notes as Gage spoke, and as he glanced up again, Gage was shocked to realize that his eyes had become brown again. Some sort of trick of the light? No, there was no &lt;em&gt;blue&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; light in the small workshop. Some kind of wizard thing, more like. He scratched his beard uncomfortably and then crossed his arms over his large chest, scowling. The little bastard was probably casting some sort of spell on his shop, and he&#x27;d have words with the mayor over this. The mayor was what Gage thought of as a &quot;fancy&quot; man- someone who&#x27;s work involved papers and meetings, rather than producing anything of value. Not unlike wizards, come to think of it. The difference, of course, was that the mayor wouldn&#x27;t reduce his shop to splinters when confronted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Thank you.&quot; Johan said, as he finished writing. He nodded deeply, almost a short bow, and then walked out of the shop without bothering to say goodbye.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gage scratched his head again as Rog sidled up to him. The two men stood in the heat of the forge and stared through the door, which had been propped open to release some of the heat, watching the wizard as he walked carelessly through the churned mud of the street, bent over his notes. They looked at each other.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Who th&#x27; hells was that?&quot; Rog said, finally.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gage grunted, still annoyed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Had papers from the mayor that said &#x27;e was a wizard. Allowed to &lt;em&gt;tour&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; any local shops an&#x27; whatnot.&quot; Gage said the word &quot;tour&quot; with a snort, and then turned back to cleaning the shop. Rog followed after him, wide-eyed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;A wizard? In &lt;em&gt;Dotton&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;?&quot; He asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Yep.&quot; Gage stacked the leftover scraps from the hinges and dropped them into a barrel by the wall.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Why?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Dunno.&quot; Gage replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;You didn&#x27;t ask?&quot; Rog said, and then backed up abruptly as Gage stood to his full height and turned on him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;No. I didn&#x27;t ask the gods-damn &lt;em&gt;wizard&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; what &#x27;is business was. I don&#x27;t know, I don&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;wanna&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; know, and if you &#x27;ad half the sense your ma thinks you &#x27;ave, &lt;em&gt;you&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; wouldn&#x27;t want to know either. Stay away from him. Stay out of his way. An&#x27; if he shows up with a piece of paper from the gods-damn &lt;em&gt;mayor&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, you do what you gotta and split as soon as you can. Understood?&quot; Gage thundered, his brow heavy with annoyance, both at his overly curious apprentice, and the frustratingly calm young man who had made his shoulders itch most of the day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rog ducked his head and muttered something that might have been &quot;sorry&quot;, &quot;yessir&quot; or some combination of the two. Mollified, Gage relented, exhaling heavily and shaking his head.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Now grab me some stock. We&#x27;ve got a plow to make.&quot; He said, in a calmer tone. Rog hurried to obey.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Media Manipulation With AI</title>
		<published>2025-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-12-media-and-ai/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-12-media-and-ai/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;broad_city_cringe.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Abbi and Ilana freak out over Hillary Clinton&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Believe it or not, no one is about to be arrested for public indecency in this scene.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, I attended the recording of a podcast called Austinprenure in Texas (episode is &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;podcasts.apple.com&#x2F;us&#x2F;podcast&#x2F;combating-disinformation-with-knowledge-graphs-and-llms&#x2F;id1446779826?i=1000670542827&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, my questions start at around the 35:00 mark). The guest described their work to trace the flow of radicalization through central europe. His description was very general (likely because much of it is classified), but from what I understand, it involved ingesting huge amounts of media content created in central europe and analyzing it for particular messages, then watching how those messages were propagated on social and traditional media to identify sources that were responsible for radicalization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My question was whether this could be done in reverse. It seems like it could. I&#x27;ve heard image generation from plain text described as just the opposite of description generation for images. While it may not be &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the reverse in a you-can-just-run-this-model-backwards sort of way, it seems obvious that if the technology exists to generate descriptions for images, then the technology &lt;em&gt;also&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; exists to generate an image from plain text descriptions. In the same way, if you have a model that can ingest media and then describe the radicalization that might result from it, then the technology &lt;em&gt;also&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; exists to describe radicalization and then generate media that pushes people toward it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A system like this might even be able to influence political and cultural views without ever producing content that would be considered political (or even relevant). In &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;slatestarcodex.com&#x2F;2014&#x2F;09&#x2F;30&#x2F;i-can-tolerate-anything-except-the-outgroup&#x2F;&quot;&gt;an old blog post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Scott Alexander, he writes-&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blue Tribe is most classically typified by liberal political beliefs, vague agnosticism, supporting gay rights, thinking guns are barbaric, eating arugula, drinking fancy bottled water, driving Priuses, reading lots of books, being highly educated, mocking American football...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems possible that making someone less interested in football might actually make them more liberal politically, in a tail-wags-dog sort of way. If someone who was a fan of the sport becomes less interested, they&#x27;ll stop hanging out with friends who are still following the game. They may have fewer parties with those friends. They may be more willing to view and read content from &lt;em&gt;other&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; people (likely liberal) who dislike the game. Their friend group may slowly shift to the left, politically. Although it&#x27;s difficult to find any research on this (if you have any, feel free to email me), just at first glance, this seems like something that could happen. The real question is- how do you reduce interest in football?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving this change in interest is hard, but not impossible. If you have control of their social media feeds (which are almost always algorithmically driven to one degree or another), you might naively assume that you could just insert some anti-football content. This is unlikely to work, because people often become more entrenched in their views when those views are challanged&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. What likely &lt;em&gt;would&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; work is providing ostensibly pro-football content that&#x27;s just... &lt;em&gt;cringe&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example of cringe, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=lJgM4_C3gvE&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is the scene in &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Broad_City&quot;&gt;Broad City&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; where I totally lost interest in the show. Not because I especially dislike Hillary Clinton, but because this level of adoration toward &lt;em&gt;any&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; politician is unsettling and cringey to me. I understand they were playing it for laughs, but I didn&#x27;t laugh. I winced.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;broad_city_comments.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Comments on the Broad City Hillary Clinton cameo&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;So did everyone else.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t want to pick on Broad City, specifically, but it was the first example that came to mind. I stopped watching the show after this scene. Did it make me more conservative? Not in any noticeable way. But what if I regularly viewed content that highlighted the most cringe-inducing, silly, or ridiculous people that share my own ideology, even while supposedly supporting them? I would like to believe that I&#x27;m immune to this sort of soft-propaganda, but I&#x27;ve met too many people who thought the same and were wrong. Given enough time, I think it might push me away from what I currently believe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just to be clear, this is only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; example of &lt;em&gt;one&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; way in which someone could be influenced. Maybe our model doesn&#x27;t generate cringe- maybe it introduces them to local organizations that are A) related to something they&#x27;re interested in, and B) already stacked with people slightly to one side of their current political alignment. Maybe it promotes content from friends they haven&#x27;t seen in a while who share &lt;em&gt;most&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of their views, but have crucial differences. Maybe they tend to match with people on Tinder that don&#x27;t like football. There is a huge space of possible ways to influence someone when you&#x27;re ingesting terabytes of data and mining it for fuzzy and exploitable relationships in order to do it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any organized attempt to do this at scale would be a massive undertaking, likely requiring access to huge amounts of user data, intimate control over the content that those users are consuming, and some serious improvements in AI technology. Unfortunately, all of those things are becoming easier with time. People are using social media more than ever before, and these platforms collect vast amounts of information on them&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, while AI is only becoming more capable&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. The feeds that people use to discover new content are almost entirely algorithmic now, with only a few platforms stubbornly clinging to chronological or category-based recommendations, and the &quot;algorithms&quot; are more likely to be AI. At the same time, people are more likely to self-sort into &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Filter_bubble&quot;&gt;isolated&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (read: vulnerable) communities that share common beliefs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be difficult, but not impossible, even with current technology. And it&#x27;s only going to become &lt;em&gt;more&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given enough data, enough control over what people see, and strong enough AI, you could build a system that generates content designed to sway an entire population into believing particular things. If such a system were controlled by the Metas and Tiktoks of the world, then it would probably be used to deliberately excise radical or undesireable elements from their platform, increase user engagement, and generate profit in various ways, all without ever doing anything that most users would recognize as manipulative. But once the tools are in place, how long would it take them to be used on behalf of the state?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media companies have already been accused of censoring or de-emphasizing political views on the right and the left. Whether any particular accusation has merit or not, it&#x27;s definitely something that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; happen. If Twitter had a tool in place that could incrementally and almost unnoticeably shift the discourse in one direction or another, I have difficulty imagining that tool not eventually being used to placate the US government.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if the content is funny and interesting, people will watch it. If, sometimes, a few people see an uptick in content that makes them roll their eyes at their own party, tribe, or demographic, who cares? It&#x27;s not like they&#x27;re going to go out and start campaigning for [insert other political party here].&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; time they see it. Or the second. But eventually? Maybe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do I think that anyone in the current administration would try to build something like this? No. This isn&#x27;t because I have faith in their essential goodness, but because I don&#x27;t think any of them understand that it&#x27;s even possible. But some people working for the military or intelligence community likely have some idea that it is, and are competant enough to build it. As the barriers continue to lower, something like this will gradually become more and more likely.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;torment_nexus.jpeg&quot;  alt=&quot;Tech company builds the Torment Nexus&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Twitter would build the Torment Nexus for a 5% bump in user retention.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond companies influencing public opinion for engagement and money, beyond governments using the same tools to manipulate and control their citizens (I&#x27;m looking at you, China), there&#x27;s the threat of rogue AI doing the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&#x27;m not a fervent believer in the rise of superintelligent artificial intelligence, I don&#x27;t entirely discount it. I&#x27;ve already discussed the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ai-2027.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;AI 2027&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; scenario in another post, and if something even vaguely similar to that scenario were to occur, this is another way that an agentic AI could manipulate public opinion. Are people pissed over losing their jobs? Are they scared of a fully autonomous economy? If tools like this exist, then any agent worth it&#x27;s compute would be able to paint dissidents as luddites and gather support without ever doing anything that a human being could point to as manipulative.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So anyway. That&#x27;s it. Enjoy the existential dread.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;...when exposed to arguments supporting positions different from their prior views, people often (though perhaps not always) become even more convinced of their prior views rather than being swayed by arguments&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;academic.oup.com&#x2F;aristotelian&#x2F;article&#x2F;123&#x2F;2&#x2F;173&#x2F;7207975&quot;&gt;Can Arguments Change Minds?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;We collect information about how you use our Products, such as the types of content you view or engage with; the features you use; the actions you take; the people or accounts you interact with; and the time, frequency and duration of your activities.&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.facebook.com&#x2F;about&#x2F;privacy&#x2F;update&#x2F;printable&quot;&gt;Facebook Data Policy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;The overall performance of LMs gets reliably better as investment increases. Rapid progress in LMs has primarily come from simply training larger models on more data&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theaidigest.org&#x2F;progress-and-dangers&quot;&gt;AI Digest&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Military AI Is More Likely Than You Think</title>
		<published>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-10-militarized-ai/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-10-militarized-ai/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;crows_platform.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;CROWS weapon platform&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Despite appearances, the CROWS weapon platform is not a friendly and lovable robot sidekick&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven&#x27;t read &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ai-2027.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;AI 2027&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, you should. It&#x27;s a story (model? scenario?) describing how superhuman AI could be created and what might happen if it is, and the authors include a huge amount of justification for their conclusions. It&#x27;s plausible, although by the end it begins to creep into the ridiculous. It might be &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; ridiculous, or I could just be falling into the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Argument_from_incredulity&quot;&gt;classic trap&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of believing that anything that seems weird to me personally can&#x27;t happen. We&#x27;ll find out around 2028 or 2030, I suppose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree strongly with one part of it though. To explain why I disagree, I&#x27;ll need to tell a story about a panel on AI safety that I attended at &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fedsupernova.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FED Supernova&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in 2024.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FED Supernova is a conference held every year in Austin, Texas. There are booths for companies that are selling unique technology to various parts of the military- everything from project management software to high tech bandages. In 2024, I was walking around the lobby when I saw a what looked like a Boston Dynamics robot with armor plating and rails (for mounting guns) attached to it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talked to the operator for a bit. He claimed they could be controlled remotely or run autonomously, were aware of other nearby units, and could move automatically in packs. They could also serve as a weapons platform for anything up to a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;FGM-148_Javelin&quot;&gt;Javelin missile&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and could handle the recoil from a .50 caliber machine gun. Fun stuff.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;fed_supernove_2024.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Tactical robot dog&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Cool as hell, even if it ends up killing us all&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017 or so when I first became aware of &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Boston_Dynamics#Spot&quot;&gt;Spot&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, the Boston Dynamics version of this robot, my first thought was &quot;if someone isn&#x27;t already working on turning that thing into a weapon, they will be shortly.&quot; Watching the weaponized version of that robot walk around the lobby during a DoD technology conference in 2024, my immediate thought was &quot;if someone isn&#x27;t already trying to automate tactical decision making for those things, they will be shortly.&quot; I&#x27;m not an expert on AI, but as far as I can tell, the technology already exists, although it might not have been assembled from the various available models and data ingestion tools.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would need to describe a battlefield in a way that an AI could understand, have a model trained on a huge number of historical engagements, and convert the output of such a model into orders for packs of robot dogs outfitted with various complementary weapons systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is possible now. Actually, all of this was possible in &lt;em&gt;2024&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, so I&#x27;d guess it&#x27;s probably being field tested somewhere now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these thoughts in my head, I went into the next panel that I was planning to attend- a discussion of AI ethics and safety. I&#x27;m, again, not an expert on either AI or the ethics and alignment issues surrounding the field, but I come in contact with people who are and sometimes read through discussion or blog posts on the topic. But even I could see that the panel wasn&#x27;t engaging with any particularly difficult questions. When they asked for questions from the audiance, I raised my hand for the microphone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a robot dog in the lobby that&#x27;s partially autonomous and capable of coordinating with other robot dogs. If the technology necessary to make autonomous tactical decisions for a fireteam of those robots doesn&#x27;t currently exist, it will very shortly. It seems likely that, after the tactical level is automated, the strategic decision making will be as well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a confrontation between approximately equal military forces, one of which must report the current state of the battlefield up a chain of command, deliberate, and then pass orders back down the chain of command, and another which can make strategic and tactical decisions immediately, with complete knowledge of the current state of the battlefield, it seems obviously true that, all other things being equal, the military force that can act more quickly is likely to win.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this, there would be immense pressure on the US military to move toward heavy automation and remove humans from the loop in order to remain competitive. Is this a discussion that people in the military are having? Do they or you consider this to be a dangerous trend? And if so, are there any plans to mitigate this danger?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panelists all smiled, looked at each other, and shrugged. We sat in silence for a moment, and then the moderator asked if any of them would like to respond. After another brief silence, in which the panelists continued to smile vaguely out at the audiance, he answered me himself. His reply was bland, reassuring, and completely missed the point of the question.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I walked away from that panel, annoyed and uneasy, it occurred to me that everyone on that panel likely had a security clearance and access to classified information about military AI efforts. Their lack of response, in a way, &lt;em&gt;was&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a response.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading through the AI 2027 scenario, my first thought was that the authors are &lt;em&gt;heavily&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; underestimating how quickly AI will be adopted by the US military. These are not people who wonder if they are falling prey to the argument from incredulity, who speculate about the dangers of superhuman AI, or who give a shit about alignment. They will nod along with whatever the AI researchers say, and then ask what the earliest expected date for a field deployment might be. The following quote, in particular, is the most improbable thing I read in this story-&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President is troubled. Like all politicians, he’s used to people sucking up to him only to betray him later. He’s worried now that the AIs could be doing something similar. Are we sure the AIs are entirely on our side? Is it completely safe to integrate them into military command-and-control networks? How does this “alignment” thing work, anyway?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only because the idea of Donald Trump soberly considering these questions is laughable, but because at this point in the story I would find it incredibly unlikely that they haven&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;already&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; integrated these agents (or military variants of them) into our command-and-control networks. We have semi-autonomous drones in the air and on the ground. We have &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;CROWS&quot;&gt;weapons systems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that can be operated remotely and automatically track movement. We have a global network of intelligence, targeting, and surveillance systems producing huge amounts of data that &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; be analyzed by human beings at a useful speed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Agent-1 in the AI 2027 scenario would be able to automate or partially automate many of these systems. By Agent-3-mini (the point where the president becomes troubled in the above quote), I would expect full tactical automation of most drones, mostly-automated targeting for most weapons platforms, and partially automated strategic planning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sincerely doubt that a future superintelligence would have to find some way to &lt;em&gt;convince&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the US government to give it control over our military forces. It seems much more likely that it will be born with that control already in place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Building An Organic MMORPG</title>
		<published>2025-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-09-mmorpgs/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-09-mmorpgs/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;wizard_casting.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;A wizard casting a spell&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Fireball level 2, same as fireball level 1 but with 23% more particle effects.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blackpath.blog&#x2F;posts&#x2F;2025-04-05-mmorpgs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I promised that I would try to lay out a way that an MMORPG could have an ever changing world. Monsters and herds of animals should slowly migrate, dungeons should change or even gradually empty and become abandoned before disappearing entirely, forests could spread or shrink as players harvest wood, and rivers would flood or even change course in response to in-game events.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is tricky, because it&#x27;s almost impossible to implement convincingly if you want to do it automatically, and game developers are understandably nervous about creating games that require constant human oversight to run. I think the dangers of building a game that has to be managed is worth the risk when it comes to MMORPGs, because these games &lt;em&gt;already&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; require constant oversight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blizzard, the company behind World of Warcraft, has ~500 developers&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; working on the game, while Sandbox Interactive (Albion Online) has 100&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; or so, according to some quick googling. These developers are &lt;em&gt;already&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; responsible for implementing new features and releases for these games. If a game could be created that is manually altered at runtime to create an organic, responsive world for players, and if that manual alteration could be overseen by a relatively small handful of dedicated game designers, then much of this ongoing development wouldn&#x27;t be necessary. The game wouldn&#x27;t require regular, major releases of new content to keep drawing players in, because the game would be gradually changing all of the time, often in response to player actions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A team of developers would still be necessary to fix bugs, gradually add or update mechanics, and improve performance, but the massive teams of developers working on new content would be unnecessary. They would be replaced by game designers working within the game world itself to manage the player experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I don&#x27;t have hard numbers on exactly what the ongoing expense would be for the company that developed such a game, I think it would at least be comparable to the costs of maintaining a more traditional MMORPG, and the difference to the players would be &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;given the opportunity, players will optimize the fun out of a game&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Soren_Johnson&quot;&gt;Soren Johnson&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In traditional MMORPGs (by which I mean &lt;em&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; existing MMORPGs), the game world is fully-knowable. This means that players gradually converge on optimal builds for characters, create patterns to optimize the grind for resources, and develop strategies for high speed leveling. Players that don&#x27;t have this deep knowledge of the game mechanics are hopelessly outmatched by players that do. This is fun in a way, because part of the fun of playing an MMORPG is gradually acquiring that knowledge. In another sense, it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;relentlessly boring&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, because once you know that an optimal path exists, you feel compelled to follow it, and more dedicated players will create (and publish) that optimal path almost immediately.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the game world is slowly, but constantly changing, it subverts this pattern. Experienced players can still be caught off guard by changes, and new players have the opportunity to discover things that even veterans don&#x27;t know or haven&#x27;t seen before.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Table top games like &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Dungeons_%26_Dragons&quot;&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; have a game master who orchestrates the world. They&#x27;re responsible for telling you where the monsters are, what the dungeons are like, and how the NPCs are behaving. The role of the game master &lt;em&gt;exists&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to keep secrets from the players- if everyone playing knew up front where the monsters were, and why the NPCs were behaving the way that they were, then the game would be boring.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why not reintroduce them to MMORPGs?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;albion_map.jpeg&quot;  alt=&quot;The world map of Albion Online&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;The world map of Albion Online with five rough regions that each have different terrain, biomes, and monsters. Image taken from a quick google search.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can divide the world map of our hypothetical game up into regions, each of which is managed by one or two game masters, and give them creative control over the dungeons, monsters, resources, and quests in their region. They would, in a way, be &quot;playing&quot; the game, except their goals would be different from that of the player. They would be trying to provide fresh and interesting experiences, to tell little stories through the game world that players can discover, and occasionally work together to tell larger narratives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficult part of doing this is creating the tools that make it possible. Game masters would need specialized software that would let them create these changes in the world and review them before they&#x27;re made available to players. Below, I&#x27;ve written a short (and incomplete) list of features that this sort of software would likely need, in no particular order:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detailed information on historical player behavior in the game&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to playtest changes inside the current game world&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools to alter terrain, place buildings, and script NPC interaction&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to review and approve each others changes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated testing to find performance and rendering issues&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Changeover triggers to automate publishing of related changes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chat and communication with other game masters&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pipeline to request and insert new assets from artists&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, there&#x27;s a catch here. The software that the game masters use to interact with the world would require development itself, which seems to contradict my earlier assertion that the ongoing development effort would be lower on an MMORPG like this. I still believe that the &lt;em&gt;ongoing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; effort would be lower, but the trade-off would be more up-front work. I don&#x27;t think that there would be as much up-front work as you might think, though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I don&#x27;t have inside knowledge about how World of Warcraft developers construct new regions or quests in the game, I assume that they have internal tools that do some of this. Most developers build tools to make their development process easier as they go along- things like map editors, quest designers, and import utilities. Rather than build these things haphazardly, I&#x27;m arguing that they could be combined into a single application and become a deliberate part of the game itself, even after launch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result would likely be worth it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dungeons would be intentional and noticeably different, they would appear as the undead dug their way out of the ground or in mines that players have long since emptied of resources. They would fade as players raid them, becoming first abandoned and then only jumbled rocks over old entrances. Herds of animals would migrate, and monsters would invade. Resources in some areas would gradually disappear as players harvest them, and be replaced by resources in new areas, or not replaced at all, leading to shortages and encouraging players to travel further afield to find new forests and mines. Orcs might invade, attacking towns that players believed to be entirely safe, or disappear suddenly, only to return as part of a horde in a different region.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game would always be different, but never randomly so- it would be different because there are global narratives on top of a hundred little stories and secrets crafted by human storytellers, each of whom is hoping that players will discover and follow those stories to the end.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(I plan to write another post discussing how this can be done from a technical perspective. I&#x27;ll add a link here when I do.)&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;...over 500 World Of Warcraft developers have voted to form their own union...&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rockpapershotgun.com&#x2F;over-500-world-of-warcraft-developers-at-blizzard-have-voted-to-form-microsofts-biggest-wall-to-wall-union&quot;&gt;RockPaperShotgun&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;...and now employ an international team of more than 100 people.&quot; - &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;albiononline.com&#x2F;jobs&quot;&gt;albiononline.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>I Remember Snow</title>
		<published>2025-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-08-snow/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-08-snow/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m thirty-seven.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live just outside of a city and often find myself driving into or out of town on a six-lane highway with a grassy median. Sometimes I listen to podcasts or music, but often I just drive and think. More than once, recently, I&#x27;ve caught myself thinking about a particular winter when I was a kid.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My childhood was strange. Not to me, but to most people that I know now. We lived in places far from other families and electricity was a luxury that we mostly did without. For a few years, we lived in the edge of a national forest, and I spent a lot of time tramping about in the woods with my siblings, playing with sticks and rocks when other kids our age were playing games and sports with friends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One winter it started snowing and just didn&#x27;t stop. It snowed for days, until every tree was bent under the weight of it. We didn&#x27;t have power or gas at the time, so our house was heated by wood and a kerosene heater. Some neighbor told my dad about a tree that had fallen down nearby, and we took a chainsaw and set out to find it, leaving the truck at home because we were on top of a mountain and the roads were dangerous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We bundled up, layering coats over knit shirts over T-shirts, and pulling my mother&#x27;s handmade toboggan caps (We called them &quot;boggans&quot;) down low over our ears before we traipsed out through knee deep snow to find the tree.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t remember much else about that little expedition. It was nothing. Barely a story. What I do remember is the deep stillness of the forest. No trucks were driving or animals stirring. The snow muffled everything and left the forest a quiet, meditative place where people were only tolerated if they could survive. Despite the roads carving through the hills, for a while, that mountain wasn&#x27;t &lt;em&gt;our&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; place. It wasn&#x27;t a place meant for people.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I drive through traffic every day, staring at slowly browning checkerboard squares of sod and close cut grass littered with cigarette butts. Every year, snow becomes more scarce and the stars are harder to see through street lamps and the ever-present glow on the horizon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I miss the snow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Player Limitations in MMORPGs</title>
		<published>2025-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-05-mmorpgs/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-05-mmorpgs/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;lvl1_mmo_characters.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;A man with a stick fighting crabs&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Just nine more giant crabs, man, and then I&#x27;ll turn in the quest, get a beginners sword and move on to killing giant rats...&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been playing a lot of &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;albiononline.com&#x2F;home&quot;&gt;Albion Online&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It&#x27;s... not very good.
That&#x27;s not to say that it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, really, but it&#x27;s just not a particularly compelling game. I&#x27;m
never caught up in thinking about the next thing I should do in the game while I&#x27;m not playing
it, or trying (and failing) to convince myself to stop playing and do something more productive.
Unlike addictive drugs and better made games, where you tell yourself (and everyone else)
that you can stop whenever you want, man, I swear- I actually &lt;em&gt;can&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; stop playing whenever I want,
because it&#x27;s just not very engaging. I described it to a friend as &quot;slightly more fun than
doing nothing at all&quot;, which about sums up the entire experience, I think.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do spend a lot of time thinking about how it could be made better, and for a while I had a document
where I was listing all of the things that could be done to make the game more compelling. Some of
those changes are listed below (if you don&#x27;t know anything about MMOs in general, or Albion Online
in particular, feel free to skip the following list).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random monsters are scattered about the map, and they attack you when you&#x27;re travelling or gathering
nearby. I would group them into camps and thin out the random individual monsters. It would make
both travelling and gathering less annoying and would look much more natural.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters attack you when you get too close, but in Albion, you have to get &lt;em&gt;very&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; close before they
attack. It looks silly, but happens accidentally all the time because there are so many of them
standing around. After I grouped them into camps, I would increase aggro distance to make camps
more dangerous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When monsters attack you, their attacks &lt;em&gt;always&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; land. This is never more noticeable and aggravating
than when you&#x27;re just running by and a golem takes a shambling swipe at you that lands when you&#x27;re
already fifty feet away. For bonus annoyance, it also removes the speed buff that you get from
riding. I would make attacks fail if you&#x27;re out of range.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recalling to town in Albion costs money based on weight and distance to town, and takes you back
to the last town you were in, rather than your home city. I would do away with this and add
craftable recall scrolls that take you home (or maybe to a particular city).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were were more notes, but you get the idea. The recall problem, in particular, was grating to me-
nothing about the game is improved by forcing players to pay increasingly large amounts to recall
based on distance or weight carried. The only real reason it would be designed that way is to
force players with no money to spend fifteen minutes running back to town, and allow players &lt;em&gt;with&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
money to avoid that annoyance. Maybe as a bid to push players toward paying real money for in-game
gold? I don&#x27;t know. And because recalling takes you back to the last city you were in, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; your
home city, if you make the mistake of walking into a strange city a long way from home, your
recall now takes you &lt;em&gt;there&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; instead of home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, recall scrolls immediately make the game more interesting. If you&#x27;re poor, you
can still avoid that run back to town with a little planning, but you have to invest some time in
crafting scrolls, which could be interesting in it&#x27;s own right. If you&#x27;re rich, of course, you can
just buy the scrolls from the auction house. If the scrolls are locked to a particular town instead
of to the home city of the player who uses them, then things get even more interesting. Players
would be able to buy scrolls for a particular city and transport them to another city to be sold for
a profit, creating a niche market in fast-travel. You could even travel to dangerous and exotic
locations to create recall scrolls and then sell them for a large profit in the main cities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Albion already has fast travel, and it&#x27;s provided by an NPC in each city who charges
you based on weight. Presumably another attempt to push players toward purchasing in-game gold with
real money.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this got me thinking about creative constraints, and how they might drive interesting gameplay
in an MMORPG.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One good example of this are maps. In most MMORPGs, there&#x27;s a world map that the player can use to get
an idea of where they are in the game, and where everything else is. It might be simplified or highly
detailed, but it&#x27;s the same level of detail for all of the players at all times. You&#x27;re using the same
map at max level as you are when you start the game. Imagine if, instead of being a constant part of
the game, the map had to be &lt;em&gt;crafted&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Now you have a bunch of new, interesting ways that the players
can interact with the game-&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New players only have the sketchiest of ideas where they are and what else is out there, which makes
the world seem big and mysterious.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Players with the appropriate skills (scouts, cartographers and the like) would become valuable as
party members because they could guide the group to dungeons or points of interest in the world.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Players who can create maps have a reliable source of income that doesn&#x27;t rely on combat ability,
&lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a good reason to go out and explore the world.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game has a new secondary market in maps of varying levels of detail, or with different features
(think enchanted maps with resource locations).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acquiring rare or highly detailed maps would give players goals to work toward that are more nuanced
and interesting than &quot;kill ten rats, XP number goes up&quot;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one small constraint on the players opens up a world of options for interesting gameplay. This could
become even more elaborate if the game designers really leaned into these new features. Players with pets could
scout an area quickly and make highly detailed maps more easily. Players with particular skills might be
able to create enchanted maps that not only show where buildings are, but have detailed information about
resources and monsters. Maps could be bought piecemeal for different regions, making the world seem mysterious
and large even to experienced players, when they venture outside of the areas where they normally play.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possiblities are endless.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of these features take time and effort on the part of the game developers, but even the
simplest, most easily implemented version of this makes the game vastly more interesting. This general approach
can be applied to any number of other cases in MMORPG game development, so much so that I feel that it&#x27;s
almost a general rule, some sort of fundamental law of game design. I would be surprised if it&#x27;s not, and I
suspect this is one of those things where an experienced and knowledgeable game designer would roll their
eyes at me and say &quot;yeah, &lt;em&gt;we know&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&quot;. I think it just strikes me like a revelation because I&#x27;m not an
experienced and knowledgeable game designer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limiting the information that a player has, then providing a way to get that information through gameplay,
makes the game more fun.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently started working on a design document for an MMORPG that I&#x27;d like to make at some point, and this
rule features prominently in that design. While I don&#x27;t think I have the technical chops to make an MMO
from scratch (in any reasonable amount of time), I needed some way to scratch the itch that I get in the back
of my head when I&#x27;m playing games that are only slightly more interesting than doing nothing at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other major component of the MMORPG design (which is codenamed &quot;Tinker&quot; because, well, it&#x27;s just me
&lt;em&gt;tinkering&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) is to build a system where the world itself is slowly but constantly changing. I think this
is something that MMORPGs in particular struggle with. World of Warcraft tries to do this by releasing new
content at regular intervals, with repeatable quests and new regions. Other games try to do this by adding
in some sort of faction warfare system where areas change hands between different (artificial, game-enforced)
groups of players. Neither of these approaches really feels right to me, and I think some more drastic
and organic system could be created that makes the game world seem more real. Vital. Flexible. Players should
&lt;em&gt;actually&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; be able to affect the world in a way that makes a good story&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They should be able to point to a place in the world and tell their friends &quot;see that overgrown hill there?
That&#x27;s the skeleton of a dragon that someone accidentally unleashed. Fifty players banded together
and took it down after it destroyed two small villages.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making that possible is the real trick, and I think I&#x27;ll be following up with another post where I describe
an approach that I think would work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Tariffs Probably Won&#x27;t Work</title>
		<published>2025-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-04-tariffs/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://blackpath.blog/posts/2025-04-04-tariffs/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;images&amp;#x2F;trumps_tariffs.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Trump holding up a list of tariffs&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Whether these tariffs are actually reciprocal or based on a misunderstanding about trade deficits is left as an exercise to the reader.&lt;&#x2F;small&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been thinking a lot about the tariffs that the Trump administration has recently put in place on imports into the US. I don&#x27;t think that they&#x27;ll work, and I think most reasonable people would probably come to the same conclusion. I know people who disagree with me though, and I thought it was important that I try to outline and clarify &lt;em&gt;why&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I don&#x27;t think the tariffs would work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies will raise the price of their products to offset the loss from the tariffs. Because the tariffs are &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.bbc.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;articles&#x2F;c1jxrnl9xe2o&quot;&gt;so large&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (25-55%), they will likely &lt;em&gt;have&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to raise their prices or go out of business, because the tariffs are larger than their profit margin. Most people understand that this will happen, but they believe that this is a short-term pain for a longer term gain. If the tariffs cost companies enough, they will bring their manufacturing facilities back to the US, providing jobs and contributing to the local economy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t believe that&#x27;s the case and think that these people are vastly underestimating how much pain the tariffs will cause.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tariffs apply to almost every country that we do business with and almost every industry that we trade in. This means that not only are &lt;em&gt;cars&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; subject to these tariffs, but the metal, plastic, and electronics that go into &lt;em&gt;making&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; cars are as well. These are called &quot;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Intermediate_good&quot;&gt;intermediate goods&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&quot;, and almost every product that we buy is manufactured from them (if there are companies that own their manufacturing process all the way from mining the raw materials to selling the products, I&#x27;ve never heard of them).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the tariffs are applied to cars, the components of the cars, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the raw materials that all of those intermediate goods are made out of. That means that even if a car manufacturer moves facilities to the US, they&#x27;ll still be paying higher prices for the upstream materials. So we just reshore the component manufacturing too, right? That will fix it, and bring even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; jobs to the US. Except the component manufacturers will still be paying higher prices for the materials that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; need to make the components, and so on. At some point, we reach economic bedrock and it becomes impossible to continue this series of moves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take semiconductors, a vital part of most modern electronic devices (including cars), as an example. 92% of the global manufacturing capability for these chips &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usitc.gov&#x2F;publications&#x2F;332&#x2F;working_papers&#x2F;us_exposure_to_the_taiwanese_semiconductor_industry_11-21-2023_508.pdf&quot;&gt;is located in Taiwan&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which was just hit with a 32% tariff on imports into the United States. These chips are made from proprietary designs using proprietary techniques, are sold globally, and were never based in the US to begin with. They will not move their production to the US and reproducing that manufacturing capability in the US would take years (if not a decade or more) to do; years in which the United States would find it impossible to make even simple electronic devices without great expense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, many of the goods affected by the tariffs are &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Elasticity_(economics)&quot;&gt;elastic&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which means that as the price increases, customers will turn to alternatives or refuse to buy the product altogether. Due to decreased demand, companies will downsize their manufacturing capability or lay off workers- there&#x27;s no point in paying people to make goods that no one is buying. This means that tariffs could &lt;em&gt;add&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; some jobs by forcing businesses to reshore their production to the states, then &lt;em&gt;cost&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; us jobs by forcing businesses to raise prices and reduce production to meet the lower demand for more expensive products.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the tariffs will likely cause companies to raise prices on their products permanently or semi-permanently, because their intermediate goods will become more expensive, which will lead (in many cases) to decreased demand and a reduction in manufacturing jobs in the US. But will they still build more factories and plants in the states?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies will be weighing the expense of building and maintaining factories in the United States (which may become entirely pointless when the tariffs are removed or reduced) against lost profits from higher prices and reduced demand. It seems clear that the optimal path, from their point of view, is to lobby for tariff exceptions and wait until the tariffs go away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they will. This or another administration will do away with them, because the alternative is a United States that is unable to compete technologically with the rest of the world. When Germany is manufacturing products with parts and electronics sourced from the best global sources at the lowest possible prices, and the United States is building lower-quality products (we have to import the expertise that the original manufacturers already have) at higher expense because we&#x27;re hobbled by artificial price controls, then Germany will sell to the world and we won&#x27;t.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, prices will increase drastically, even for products that are primarily manufactured in the United States already (due to the higher cost for intermediate goods), which will lower demand, leading to fewer jobs. The companies most affected by the tariffs just have to wait out the tariffs, which they &lt;em&gt;can&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, because permanent tariffs would lead to a crippled US economy relative to the rest of the world, and a future administration would likely understand this. In the meantime, they can lobby for exceptions and make token moves to placate the US government.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why I don&#x27;t believe that the tariffs will work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>